(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-07T12:53:32.945154",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
のっじゃーー！
Nojjaaa!
あちちめらー！
Achichi Mela!
アホライブ遊び回りたいゴリ押し担当のヒャシヤサラマンダー、あちちめらなんだのっじゃー！
I'm Achichi Mela, the gorilla-pushing leader of Aho Live, nojjaa!
本日2回行動ですのっじゃー！
Today I'm doing two streams, nojjaa!
のっじゃ。
Nojja.
のじゃばんわー、のじゃばんわー……
Nojabanwa, nojabanwa...
嬉しいのっじゃー！
I'm so happy, nojjaa!
お仕事お疲れ様なっじゃー！初見のじゃ？初見のじゃやったのっじゃー！
Good job with work, nojja! First time, nojja? Yay, first time, nojjaa!
秋葉原でスタートデッキ、あっ、わしのスタートデッキあちちめら予約してくれたのありがとなっじゃー！
Thank you so much for reserving my start deck in Akihabara, nojjaa!
映画見てた？いい日なのっじゃー。
You were watching a movie? What a good day, nojjaa.
お仕事の神が多い。インフルだから毎日見れる。安心にするのじゃインフルのときは横になるのっじゃー。
You came home? Work gods are plentiful. Make sure to lie down for the flu, nojjaa.
先輩のライブ帰り、ライブお疲れ様なっじゃー楽しかった？
Coming back from senpai's stream, good job, was it fun, nojjaa?
グッズ頼んだ？グッズやったのっじゃーありがとなっじゃー！
Ordered merch? Yay for merch, nojjaa, thank you nojjaa!
テスト勉強しながら見てる？勉強になるか分かんないけれど、わしの配信を見て捗るといいな。
Watching while studying for tests? I hope watching my stream helps you get things done.
アーカイブ見てた？やったのっじゃーありがとなっじゃー！
You were watching the archive? Yay, thank you nojjaa!
秋葉原の隠れんぼまだやってるの？まだ、あっ、なんかお店に、なんかわしたちの幟とかが置いてくれてるみたいなの見たのっじゃ。
Still doing Akihabara hide-and-seek? I saw stores put up banners of us, nojja.
レベル999の村人？え、わしが知ってるやつかな？それおもろいよね。
Level 999 villager? Eh, is that the one I know? That's funny, right?
多分知ってる読んだことある気がするのっじゃ。
I feel like I've probably read it, nojjaa.
ミームの勉強になるかも。今日の配信ミームの勉強になるかもしれない。ふむふむ。
Might be good for studying memes. Today's stream might be good for studying memes, hmm.
朝の寝坊したからアーカイブで見た。え、嬉しいのっじゃーありがとなっじゃー！
Overslept in the morning so I watched the archive. I'm so happy, thank you nojjaa!
アーカイブで見る方がハードルが高いと思ってて。だから嬉しいのっじゃーありがとなっじゃー！
Watching the archive feels like a higher hurdle, so I'm so happy, nojjaa!
漏れの…漏れのことって何かしりー…
What does leaking mean...
ちょっと待て、なんかルンバが動き始めた音がした。
Wait, I think I heard the Roombas start moving.
なんか、あの、女の人の声聞こえたらルンバじゃから、いや、切ってくるか。
If I hear a woman's voice, it's a Roomba, so... wait, should I go stop it?
ちょ、ちょ、ちょっと待つのか。ちょっと待つのかじゃ。
Hold on, hold on. Wait a second, huh.
ルンバが動き始めた。
The Roomba started moving.
まただよ。
Again.
ちょっと何しとん、こいつ。
What is this guy doing?
何しとんのじゃ。
What are you doing?
おっしゃあ！のじゃあ！
Alright! Noja!
閉じ込めてきた、のじゃあ！閉じ込めてきたのじゃあ！
I locked it up, noja! I locked it away, noja!
ルンバあ！ルンバが喋り始めてびっくりした。
Roomba! I was surprised when the Roomba started talking.
なんか、あの…
It's like, um...
走ってる最中に充電が切れて、充電が切れて、充電が多分完了して再度走り直すをして、あの、走り出す音がしたから、ちょっと、かごに…
While running, its battery ran out, and after charging, it started running again, and since I heard it running, I put it in the basket...
かごに入れてきた。ルンバに名前つけてない。
and put it away. I haven't named the Roomba.
何つけようかな。
What should I name it?
そう、でも配信中だとうるさいからね、うるさいからあの、どかしてきたのじゃ。
Yeah, but it's noisy during the stream, so I moved it out of the way.
うん、働こうとしてた。のじゃ。
Yeah, it was trying to work. Noja.
さて、今日やるゲーム、お主ら、見たことある？
Now then, the game we're playing today, have you guys seen it?
今日は「手垢の、手垢のついたことしか言わない彼女」っていうゲームで遊んでいこうと思うんじゃが、
Today, we're going to play a game called "A girlfriend who only says cliché things," but
思うンじゃが、どういうゲームかというと、あの…
I think, as for what kind of game it is, um...
なんだろう、恋愛ゲーム？恋愛シミュレーションゲームっていうんじゃろか、ギャルゲー的な感じでなんか選択肢を選べる系のゲームっぽくて、
What is it, a romance game? A romance simulation game, I suppose? It feels like a galge where you can choose options, and
なんじゃが、あの…普通のゲームはさ、またただ女の子攻略するじゃん、攻略する感じだと思うんじゃが、あの…今回ノベルゲー？それじゃノベルゲー、
anyway, um... ordinary games, you just conquer a girl, right? You conquer her, but um... this time a novel game? Then a novel game,
うん、なんじゃが、あの…なんと、今回登場する女の子のキャラクターがインターネットで擦られきった浅いネタしか喋らないらしくて、
Yeah, but, um... surprisingly, the girl character appearing this time only speaks shallow internet-memed tropes, and
そう…恋愛ゲーやったことないのじゃ。
So... I've never played a romance game.
ちなみに、なんか、あの…ノベルゲー的なの、多分初見。
By the way, um... novel game-style, probably my first time.
やったことない気がするのじゃ、あるかな？
I feel like I've never played one, is there?
多分、記憶にある限りない気がする。初めての、初めての女の子攻略が、あのネットで擦られきった浅いネタしか喋らない
I probably don't have any in my memory. My first ever girl conquest only speaks shallow internet-memed tropes,
感じになっっぽい。わしなのじゃ。
feeling like it. It's Washi.
わしなのじゃ。
It's Washi.
多分これ、わしのことなのだ。初めてがこれなのだ。
This is probably about Washi. My first time is this.
で、話つまんなくなったら帰っていいらしい。
And, if the conversation gets boring, it seems I can go home.
そう、こいつ浅いことしか話さんやん。おもんなって思ったら、
Yeah, this guy only talks about shallow things. If you think it's boring,
あの、帰っていいらしいのじゃ。
um, apparently you can go home.
でもね、どうしてもわしね、これってわしのことだって思っちゃって、
even so, Washi somehow... thinking this is about Washi,
ちょっとね、ここで帰られると傷つくのじゃ。
I'd be hurt if you went home right here.
なんか、なんかね、ちょっとミニ覚えがあって、
Somehow, I have a bit of a mini-memory,
うん、ミニ覚えがあるから、ちょっと、帰りたくない！
Yeah, since I have a mini-memory, I kinda don't want to go home!
できるだけ、そう、自分で自分を突き放せないのじゃ。
As much as possible, yeah, I can't push myself away.
そう、他人事とは思えない。
Yeah, I can't think of it as someone else's problem.
確かに共感性羞恥みたいなのもあると思うんじゃが、
It's true there's also something like empathic embarrassment, but
うわ、恥ずかし！うわ！
Wow, how embarrassing! Wow!
こういう時期あった！痛い痛い痛い恥ずかしいのじゃってなっちゃうかもしれないけど、
I had a phase like this! Painful, painful, painful, it might become "how embarrassing, noja," but
そう、まるで自分を見ているようで恥ずかしくなっちゃうけど、そこまで帰っちゃったらさ、
yeah, it gets embarrassing as if looking at myself, but if you go home by that point,
あの、かつてのわしを傷つけているのと同義。そう、
um, that's synonymous with hurting the past Washi. Yeah,
わしもさ、過去のわしをも否定することになるじゃろ？
Washi too, would be denying my past self, right?
帰ると自分にダメージが入るんじゃよ。
Going home inflicts damage on yourself.
だから、もうほらげ、確かに。
So, already horage, indeed.
だから、できるだけ帰りたくない！できるだけ帰りたくない！
So, I want to avoid going home as much as possible! I want to avoid going home as much as possible!
救いたい！
I want to save them!
過去の自分を救いたいのだじゃ。
I want to save my past self, da ja.
過去の自分を向き合って救って
Face my past self, save it,
全部受け入れる配信
and accept everything in this stream!
に…したいのじゃ。
I… want to do that.
うん。
Yeah.
なのじゃ。
That's right.
いや、ちょっと心が苦しいけど
Well, my heart hurts a bit, though,
心が苦しいけど
my heart hurts a bit,
やっていこうと思うのじゃ。
but I'm going to do it anyway!
え、さすがに女の子とのデートでお面つけてるの失礼かな。
I mean, isn't it kind of rude to wear a mask on a date with a girl?
で、デート、デートってやっぱ、あの
And a date, on a date, well, you know,
お顔全部見せた方がいいのかな。どうじゃろ？
should I show my whole face? What do you think?
超失礼？外した方がいい？ど、どう思う？
Super rude? Should I take it off? Wh-what do you think?
おしゃれ？おしゃれかも。おしゃれかめよ、確かに。
Stylish? Maybe stylish. It might be stylish, true.
ミステリアスでいい。失礼？
Mysterious is fine. Rude?
落とせるかな、これで。
Can I pull it off with this?
不審者？
Suspicious?
え、でも、不審者じゃけど横に女の子いたら許される切なくない？
Eh, but even if I look suspicious, if there's a girl next to me, is that forgivable?
わし一人じゃったら不審者じゃけど、なんか横に女の子がいるだけで
If I'm alone I'm suspicious, but just having a girl next to me
なんか大体、許される感じある。
kind of makes it mostly forgivable, I feel.
マッチアップのデートなんてマスクしてるからええ。そんなもんなのじゃ？
Match-app dates have us wearing masks anyway, so is it really like that?
人間のデートはマスクしてるもんなのじゃ？
Do people wear masks on human dates too?
不審者は否定しない？
You're not denying I'm suspicious?
じゃって、髪から炎出てたら不審者じゃろうとは思うからあんま否定できないのじゃ。
I mean, if flames are coming out of my hair, people would think I'm suspicious, so I can't really deny it.
えー、お前らわしの可愛いお顔見たい？可愛いお顔見たい？
Hey guys, do you want to see my cute face? Do you want to see my cute face?
見たい？見せて欲しい？自分はどっちでもいい？
Want to see? Want me to show you? You guys don't care either way?
のじゃあ！のじゃあ！
No ja! No ja!
見たーいって言って欲しいのじゃあ！見た人がいっぱい！見せてあげますのじゃあ！
I want you to say "I want to see"! Lots of people want to see! I'll show you!
じゃあ、お部屋移動するからお前ら、高評価をして待ってて欲しいのじゃあ！行くのじゃあ！
Well then, I'm moving rooms, so you guys hit that like button and wait for me! Here we go!
ん？どうやって外す？ほ！
Hmm? How do you take it off? Ho!
遅かった。遅かったのじゃ。
I was too late. Too late.
よし、それじゃあBGMを付けますのじゃ。よいしょ。
Alright, then I'll turn on the BGM. Here we go.
音量どうかな？大きいかな？
How's the volume? Is it too loud?
大きい。ちっちゃいがあったら押して教えて欲しいのじゃ。ちょっと大きいかな？
If there's too loud or too soft, please tell me... Is it a bit too loud?
この画面からすでにきつい。そ、そんな？
It's already tough just from this screen. R-really?
いい感じ？
Feeling good?
多分、よい、ちょうどいい。よし、途中でなんか気づいたら教えて欲しいのじゃ。
Probably good, just right. Alright, if you notice anything halfway through, let me know.
はい、こちらが今回の、今回の配信、てあかノ。「手垢のついたことしか言わない彼女」
Yes, this is this stream's, this stream's "Teakano." "The girlfriend who only says cliché things."
インターネットでこすられきった、あっさいミームしか喋らない彼女っぽいんだが、インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですね。
She's like a girlfriend who only talks in shallow memes worn out on the internet, but it's like a dream you have when you have the flu.
この顔で？この顔で？この顔で？
With this face? With this face? With this face?
ちょっとなんか、ドキドキさせそうだなさ。
It makes your heart beat a little, you know.
ねえ、距離感もきっと近くてさ、近いさ、距離近くてドキドキするシチュエーションでさ、
Hey, the distance is surely close, too, close distance where your heart beats in a close situation, you know,
ねえ、私、丸々君のこと気になってるみたいですみたいなさ、顔をしながらさ、インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですね。
Hey, "It seems like I'm interested in so-and-so-kun," making a face like that, it's like a dream when you have the flu.
ハート？ハート？
Heart? Heart?
このセリフでハート？
Heart with this line?
なんじゃ？何が起きたらこのセリフが日常生、あんまこのセリフ出てくることなくなない？
What the? What has to happen for this line to—in daily life, you don't really have this line come up, do you?
ていうか、なんかあんまり日常生活でミーム言う機会ない気がするのじゃ。
I feel like you don't really have chances to say memes in daily life.
よくわかんない。そんなミームあった？
I don't really get it. Was there such a meme?
ミームというか、割とネットでこすられきった表現ではないのかの。インフルエンザのときの夢みたい。ネットでこすられきった表現に対応してくれるコラらしい。
Or rather, isn't it an expression worn out on the internet? Like a dream when you have the flu. It seems to accommodate expressions worn out on the internet.
言わない？わし聞いたことあるよ、インフルエンザのときの夢みたいですねみたいな。
You wouldn't say that? I've heard it before, like "It's like a dream when you have the flu" and stuff.
そう、Twitterのノリで話してくる人。なんか、あの、関係値のうっさいネットのフォロワーとエンカした時ってこんな感じ。
Right, people who talk with Twitter vibes. Like, when you encounter a noisy net follower with whom you have a thin relationship, it's like this.
なんか、ネットのさ、あの、いいねとか送り合うくらいのさ、あんま会話したことないおはようリプとかしかさ、
Like, on the net, like exchanging likes, we've never really talked, only morning replies or something—
あの、やり取りしないフォロワーとさ、あった時さ、話すこと本当になくてさ、話すこと本当になくて、こういうなんかし、こういうことしか言えない。
When you meet a follower you don't usually interact with, you literally have nothing to talk about, nothing at all, so you can only say stuff like this.
そんなことしか言えないのじゃ
"That's all you can say?"
そんな人と会うな。
Don't meet someone like that.
確かに。
True.
お主らインターネット防災訓練受けなおすのじゃ。
You guys need to retake your internet disaster training.
そんな価値観の浅い層会っちゃダメなのじゃ。
You shouldn't meet people with such shallow values.
確かに。
True.
話すことない人と会うな！
Don't meet people you have nothing to talk about with!
確かに。
True.
めらちゃんのワンオーワンが怖くなってきた。
Mela-chan's 1-on-1s are starting to scare me.
いや、ワンオーワンする頃には、さわしとお主らの間に思い出ができるじゃろ。
Well, by the time you do a 1-on-1, you'll have memories with Sawashi.
思い出が皆無のフォロワーと会った時にこういう会話が発生するんじゃよ。
This kind of conversation happens when you meet a follower you have zero memories with.
え、ってことはさ、この女の子とさ、あの、俺くん？俺くん？僕？なんじゃろ。
Wait, does that mean with this girl... Orekun? Orekun? Boku? I wonder.
主人公もしかしてあんまり価値観が育まれてないのでは。
Could it be that the protagonist hasn't really developed their values yet?
てか、そうじゃない？インターネットミームでしか会話できないってさ、結構価値観ない
I mean, right? Only being able to talk in internet memes means you have pretty much no values.
結構価値観ないのにもかかわらず、デート？
Even without much of a worldview, going on a date?
なんじゃ？
What is this?
何をしていらっしゃる？
What are they doing?
何をしていらっしゃるか、え、彼女って書いてるけど付き合ってるのかな？
What are they doing... Wait, it says "girlfriend," so are they dating?
付き合ってこのセリフ？「ですね」だって。
Saying this while dating? "I see," she says.
まあでも、あれか、付き合っても敬語キャラはいっか。
Well, even if they're dating, polite characters are fine, I guess.
お互い距離感誤ってそうなカップル、確かに。
A couple whose sense of distance is probably off. True.
じゃ、俺くんも彼女ちゃんも両方ともインターネットではよく喋るけど、リアルだとなかなか喋れない。
So both Orekun and Kanojo-chan talk a lot on the internet, but can't really speak in real life.
や、やめてほしいのじゃ！そんなこと言わないでほしいのじゃ！
S-Stop it! Please don't say things like that!
傷つきますのじゃ、さすがに！さすがに傷つきますのじゃ！のじゃのじゃのじゃのじゃ
It hurts, seriously! It really hurts! Noja noja noja!
はあ、ふう、ふう。
*Sigh*... Whew...
これってわしのことだ。
This is about me.
これってわしのことだ、もう帰りたい。もう帰りたい。もう帰りたいのじゃ。
This is about me, I wanna go home already. I wanna go home. I wanna go home!
もう帰るボタンない？まだない。まだ帰るボタンがない。
Isn't there a "go home" button? Not yet. There's still no go home button.
まだ付き合い立て、確かに。ほやほやのね。付き合い立てほやほやでこんなこと言っていいんか？
Still newly dating, true. Brand new. Is it okay to say stuff like this when you've just started dating?
帰れるかのう。
I wonder if I can go home.
よしじゃあ初めて行きますか。最初から。よし。
Alright then, shall we start? From the very beginning. Okay.
プレイヤー名を入力、何にしようかな。めらとかにする？めら。
Enter player name... What should I make it? Mela or something? Mela.
のじゃ、のじゃ君とかでもいいけど。
Noja, Noja-kun or something would be fine too, but...
一旦めらか。めらお？
Let's go with Mela for now. Merao?
めらおにするか。やっぱわし男の子じゃからな。めらおにするか。
Let's go with Merao. After all, I'm a boy. Let's make it Merao.
めらお行くか。わしめらお。めらお行くのじゃ。
Should I go with Merao? I'm Merao. I'm going with Merao.
オッケー。めらおなのじゃ。
Okay. I am Merao.
一人称を選んでください。俺、僕、私、自分、ウチ、自分の名前。
Choose your first-person pronoun. Ore, boku, watashi, jibun, uchi, own name.
ああ、ワシがない。でもワシない、ワシ。ワシない。
Ah, "washi" isn't there. But there's no washi. There's no washi.
自分の名前かな。一人称めらおでいくのじゃ。
My own name, I guess? I'll go with Merao for my pronoun.
めらおでいかせていただこうと思うのじゃ。さすがにワシないか。
I think I'll let Merao handle it. As expected, no washi, huh?
この年齢の中高生とかかな？高校生とかの女の子とお付き合い、ワシが和解したらまずいか。
Middle or high schoolers around this age? Dating a high school girl... would it be bad if I got involved?
ワシ410歳じゃから一旦400歳が未成年とデートやばいか。
I'm 410 years old, so a 400-year-old dating a minor might be bad, right?
やばいか？のじゃ。オッケーのじゃ。
Is that bad? Noja. Okay, noja.
それでは行きますのじゃ。オッケー。
Then let's go, noja. Okay.
一人称めらおもきつい。
Using "Merao" as a pronoun is also tough.
そんな、あ！始まりましたのじゃ。シチュエーションは駅。
Oh! It started, noja. The situation is a train station.
駅で待ち合わせしてる感じかのう。
Looks like we're meeting up at the station.
めらお、栗志江（くりしえ）さん、まだ来てないな。
Merao: Kurishie-san isn't here yet.
栗志江さんっていう感じ。栗志江ってなんで栗志江なんじゃ？くりしえ。
Kurishie-san... Why is Kurishie named Kurishie? "Cliché."
なんかこういう系の名前ってさ、割と由来あるじゃん。
Names like this usually have some kind of origin, right?
栗志江？栗志江って何？栗志江って何？わし知らない。
Kurishie? What is Kurishie? What is Kurishie? I don't know.
わしそれの元ネタ知らない。
I don't know the reference behind that.
フランス語で使い古された言い回しのこと。なるほど。
It's a worn-out phrase in French. I see.
栗志江モカさん。使い古された栗志江の、栗志江っぽい。
Kurishie Moka-san. A worn-out Kurishie, very Kurishie-like.
栗志江モカさん。めらおと同じ1年A組のクラスメイト。
Kurishie Moka-san. A classmate of Merao's in Class 1-A.
成績優秀で可憐で、物腰も穏やか。入学時点ですでに「いいね……」と話題になっていた。
Excellent grades, lovely, and gentle-mannered. Already the talk of the school since enrollment.
あ、いるよね、高嶺の花的なね。高嶺の花的なお顔も可愛いしね。髪もロングで清楚そう。
Ah, there's always someone like an out-of-reach flower. Cute face, long hair, looks neat.
1学期が始まって2週間。なかなか話しかけるタイミングがなかったけど…
Two weeks into the first term. I never really had the chance to talk to her, but...
映画に誘ったら、なんとOKをもらった。ちょいちょいちょい、めらお、距離感！距離感なのだじゃ！
When I invited her to a movie, she actually said yes! Hey hey hey, Merao, your distance! Your sense of distance!
今日を機に仲良くなれたらいいな！
I hope we can become good friends starting today!
でめらおさ、こういうとこじゃよ。なんか高嶺のさ、花のさ、
And Merao, this is why... Like, the flower of the high peak...
ねえ、栗江さん
Hey, Kurishie-san,
いいなって思って、関係値特にないのに映画に誘う、このキョ、距離感、コミュニケーションの距離感のバグり方、
Thinking she's nice and inviting her to a movie with zero relationship—the way this distance, this communication distance is so bugged,
オタクくんさあ、でもこうしないとあの時点自体というのは発展しませんね。
Oh you otaku... But if you don't do this, the situation itself won't progress.
うん、発展しないからぐいぐい。
Yeah, it won't progress unless you push forward.
メラオチャラ男なのちょっと嫌なのじゃ。
Merao being a playboy is kind of annoying.
メラオチャラ男なのじゃ。何の映画見るんじゃろ。
Merao is such a playboy. I wonder what movie they're watching.
にしても……なんかめっちゃキモい。
Even so... this is super creepy.
なんね、このあの色がすごい禍々しい色。
What is this? The colors are so ominous.
なんか平成のお土産コーナーとかにいた。
It looks like something from a Heisei-era souvenir shop.
平成の女子高生がカバンにこぞって付けてたような色味とキミョウさ。なんだじゃこれ。
The color scheme and weirdness look like what Heisei high school girls swarmed to put on their bags. What is this?
地底川ではないのじゃ間違いないなく。
It's definitely not an underground river.
改札前のオブジェ、何なんだろう。
I wonder what this object in front of the ticket gate is.
待ち合わせ場所にはいいけど、確かにこんだけね？こんだけ目立ったらね？
It's a good meeting spot, but sure, standing out this much?
ほら、なんて呼ぶんだろう。なんかさ、改札前で待ち合わせする時さ、〇〇前で待ち合わせねって言われるけどさ、これなんて名付けられるんだろな。
See, what would you call it? When meeting at a ticket gate, people say "meet in front of X," but what would this be named?
このオブジェ、何というか……
This object, how should I put it...
なんというか何？
Put it how?
いや、やめとこ。
No, never mind.
え、もしかしてこれがインフルの時に見る夢？
Wait, is this a fever dream from having the flu?
なにこれ？んなのじゃ？
What is this? What is it?
なんとじゃこれ。
What on earth is this?
栗江ちゃん来た！栗江ちゃん来たのじゃ！めらおなのじゃ！
Kurishie-chan's here! Kurishie-chan is here! It's Merao!
おはよう。栗江さん、私服だ！
Morning. Kurishie-san is in casual clothes!
確かにいつも制服しか見えないのにね、私服だとね、新鮮で可愛いのお。
True, we usually only see her in uniform, so casual clothes feel fresh and cute.
電車遅れてた？
Was the train late?
いえ、駅の中で迷っていました。確かに。駅ってね、知らん駅とかだとね、ひとおきでね迷っちゃうよね。
No, I was lost inside the station. True. In stations you don't know, you easily get lost in a single glance.
都会の駅って迷宮みたいじゃないですか？
Don't city stations feel like labyrinths?
ああ、これも確かにネットでよく聞く。あの新宿駅とかね、渋谷駅とかね。迷路じゃよな。そう、渋谷駅から出られない。そうそうそうそうそう。
Ah, I definitely hear that online a lot. Shinjuku Station, Shibuya Station... It's a maze. Yeah, you can't escape Shibuya Station. Exactly.
わかるー！
I know, right!
これ？
This?
出たのじゃ、これ。
It appeared, this thing.
出たのじゃこれ。
There it is.
なんというか……まるで……
How should I say... It's just like...
キュピーンじゃねえよ！キュピーン言ったのじゃ！話す時キュピーン言ったのじゃ！
Don't 'chime'! It went 'chime'! It made a chime sound while talking!
これがインフルエンザの時の夢？
Is this a fever dream from the flu?
え、実際どう？実際どう？
Wait, how is it really? How is it really?
インフルエンザの時の夢ってさ、もっと空間じゃない？固形物じゃなくない？
Aren't flu dreams more spatial? Not solid objects?
インフルエンザの時に見る夢ってさ、こう、なんかすっごいグラデーションの色地のさ、サイケデリックな色のさ、空間にない？空間じゃない？個体じゃなくない？なんだじゃ？
In dreams you see when you have the flu, aren't they like, a space with incredible color gradients and psychedelic colors? Not a solid entity?
うん。
Yeah.
ただし、右上に「帰る」ボタンが表示されている間プレイヤーはいつでも「帰る」ことができます。あ、帰れるんだね。帰りたくなったらボタンを押してください。うん。
However, while the 'Go Home' button is displayed in the top right, players can return anytime. Oh, you can go back. Press it if you want to leave.
1日は4つのチャプターに分かれており、どのチャプターで帰るかで、5つのエンドに分岐します。ほーー、なるほど。
Each day is split into 4 chapters, branching into 5 endings depending on when you leave. Ooh, I see.
通常の選択肢でエンディングは変わらないので好きなものをお選びください。
Normal choices don't change the ending, so choose whatever you like.
あ、選択肢は何でもいっぱいなのじゃ。帰るタイミングで分岐が有るけ。
Ah, choices are plenty. It branches based on when you go home.
はいはいはい。
Right, right, right.
もう帰れるよ、のしら。
We can already go home, you know.
もう帰れるよ。もう帰れるよ。どうする？もういいか？
We can go home already. What do should we do? Is this enough?
一旦価値観の違いで帰るか？あの、インフルエンザの時の夢は絶対に固形じゃないのじゃ。映画はいく、確かに。確かに確か映画とかは行くか。
Should we go home over a difference in values? Flu dreams are definitely not solid. We are going to a movie, true. True, we're going to a movie.
ま、かわいいしな。可愛い女の子が変なこと言っててもギリ許せるしな。
Well, she's cute. Even if a cute girl says weird things, I can barely forgive it.
（さっきめらおが思いとどまったことおまえも思ったんかい！めらおも思ったらしいのじゃ。）
(Did you also think what Merao hesitated about earlier? Seems Merao thought of it too.)
どっちがいいのか？
Which one is better...?
うん。
Yeah.
メラとクリシェさんはどうかさておき、メラおはね、
Putting Mera and Cliche aside for a moment, Merao...
思っほいっぽいからお似合いなのじゃ。お似合いカップルですのじゃ。
looks into it, so you guys match. A matching couple!
うん。
Yeah.
高熱の時って、複雑で変なものが夢に出てきたりしませんか？
When you have a high fever, don't weird, complex things appear in your dreams?
なんてドヤ顔なんだよ！
What a smug face!
なんて、なんてお前そのドヤ顔になれるんだよ！自信満々なのじゃ。
How can you make such a smug face?! So full of confidence.
まあ、まあ可愛いか。まあ、
Well, I guess she's cute. Well...
可愛い女の子がわけわかんないこと言ってたら可愛いか。
A cute girl saying random nonsense is pretty cute, right?
もしかして、比喩として斬新過ぎたでしょうか？
Could it be that my metaphor was too original?
この子斬新過ぎだと思ってます！インフルエンザの時の夢でとやって斬新過ぎだと思ってる！
She totally thinks it's too original! Dreaming about influenza and thinking it's way too out there!
ちょっと可愛い。ちょっと可愛いな。斬新過ぎたでしょうか？
Kind of cute. Kind of cute, actually. "Too original?"
え、どっちがいいんだ？そうかも。そうかもで、褒め？そうかもが褒めなのはじゃ？
Uh, which one is better? "Maybe." Is "Maybe" a compliment? Is it?
そんなことないよはディス？そんなことないよはディス？
Is "No way" an insult? Is "No way" an insult?
でも、そんなことないよの方が共感？どっちだ？そうかもの方が好感度上がるか？
But "No way" shows more empathy? Which one? Does "Maybe" raise affection more?
一旦そうかもか。
Let's go with "Maybe" for now.
言われてみれば珍しい例えかもね。
Now that you mention it, it's a rare metaphor.
高熱の時に変わった夢を見る人はあまりいないのでしょうか……？
Do very few people have strange dreams when they have a high fever...?
いる、いる。わしも見るよ。わしも変な夢見る。でもわしだいたい炎上する。
There are, there are. I see them too. I have weird dreams too. But I usually get cancelled in them.
わしの悪夢だいたい炎上する夢なのはじゃ。とかなんか、
My nightmares are mostly about getting cancelled. Or like...
あの自分の意識がないまま、あのなんか良くないことツイートしちゃって、追撃できない夢とか……。
tweeting bad stuff while I'm not conscious and not being able to delete it...
うーん、そういう夢なのはじゃ。うーん、
Yeah, that kind of dream. Yeah...
日の字にできてない夢。うーん。結構怖い夢見るのじゃ。
Dreams where I can't look straight. Yeah. I have pretty scary dreams.
空気が悪い……別の話しないと！のじゃ。
The atmosphere is bad... We need to talk about something else!
ま、まだ時間あるしスタバ行く？
W-We still have time, want to go to Starbucks?
ああ、デートっぽい！デートっぽい！映画までの間にスタバ。うんうんうん。
Ah, feels like a date! Feels like a date! Starbucks before the movie. Yeah, yeah, yeah.
新作はチョコミントだって！
The new flavor is chocolate mint!
ああ、そういうシーズンあるよね。のじゃ。
Ah, right, that season is here.
スタバ！？あの……！
Starbucks?! Um...!
てかさ、このクリシェさんさ、所作がお嬢様っぽいからさ、あんまスタバとか行ったことなさそう。
Also, Cliche has such lady-like manners, she probably hasn't been to Starbucks much.
お嬢様キャラっぽくない？
Doesn't she seem like an ojou-sama character?
歯磨き来るかな。どうせ歯磨きことか言うんじゃろ！
I wonder if she'll mention toothpaste. She's gonna say something like toothpaste anyway!
絶対歯磨きこ言う。ねえ、読んできたのこのこの子の思考。
She'll definitely say toothpaste. Did I read this girl's mind?
スタバって注文が呪いみたいなやつでしょ？これ霊長だろ！これ霊長じゃろ！
"Starbucks has orders that sound like curses, right?" That's reciting! That's reciting!
なんか、なんかさ、いや、分かるよ。わしもね、わしもね、人間で学生の頃ね、
Look, I get it. Back when I was a human student...
あの人間の中学・高校時代にね、スタバ霊長してた時期あったけどね。
in my middle and high school days as a human, there was a time I used to recite Starbucks stuff.
霊長してた時の決めゼリフが、あれでしょ？注文が呪いみたいなやつじゃろだからね。
The catchphrase back then was "orders sound like curses," you know.
はあ、もう、もう！もう……！恥ずかしい！やな記憶、やな記憶。
Ah, jeez, no! No...! So embarrassing! Such bad memories, bad memories.
なんか、クラスメイトが、なんかスタバに行くとかさ、そういうイベントがあってわし誘ってもらえなくて、それが悲しくて霊長してたのじゃ。
Some classmates had an event going to Starbucks and didn't invite me, and I was sad so I kept reciting that stuff.
誘ってもらえないのが悲しくて、あー、あのなんか呪いみたいなやつじゃろみたいな。
It was sad not being invited, so like, "Ah, that's like a curse..."
あー……！帰っていい？のじゃ。
Ah...! Can I go home?
帰っていいのじゃ？ちょっとつら、辛く、辛くなってきた。辛くなってきたのじゃ……！
Can I go home? It's getting painful, painful... It's getting so painful...!
いや、耐える。耐える耐える耐える。
No, I'll endure. Endure, endure, endure.
ちょっと、いったん、いったん最後まで見るか。
Let's watch until the end first.
出た！
There it is!
あと個人的な価値観ですけど、チョコミントって歯磨き粉みたいでちょっと……。
Also, from a personal standpoint, chocolate mint tastes a bit like toothpaste...
そういうこと言っちゃう！そういうこと言っちゃう！
She went and said it! She went and said it!
わしチョコミント割と好きじゃけど、苦手ではない。苦手ではないけど……。
I actually quite like chocolate mint. It's not that I hate it. Not that I hate it, but...
これさ、モカちゃんさ、クリシェさんさ、あのメラオくんがさ、チョコミント大好きなチョコミントじゃったらどうしてたんだ？
Look here, Moka, Cliche... What would you do if Merao-kun absolutely loved chocolate mint?
火だねじゃよ、これ！これ火だね！
That's a hazard right there! That's a hazard!
これ火だねなのだじゃ。炎上するのじゃ！
That's a fire hazard. It's gonna cause a firestorm!
配信者がこれ言ったら、あの、場合によっては、ご時世によっては燃える可能性があるセリフですのじゃ。
If a streamer said this, depending on the times, it's a line that could get them canceled.
ま、でも一般一般高校生じゃからね。うん。
Well, but they're just normal high schoolers. Yeah.
のじゃ。注文はメラオがするよ！チョコミント以外にも色々あるし！うん。
"Merao will place the order! There are other things besides chocolate mint!" Yeah.
あ、メラオできる男。フォロー、フォロー、フォロー。
Ah, Merao is such a capable guy. Follow, follow, follow.
はい。ありがとうございます。注文までしていただいて。メラオさんってとても優しいんですね！
Yes. Thank you very much. For making the order too. Merao-san, you're so kind!
あ、好感度上がった！なんか好感度上がった！
Ah, affection went up! Affection went up!
のじゃ、なんか上がった、やった！
Noja, my affection went up, yay!
あはは……気にしないで
Ahaha... don't worry about it.
黒志江さんって、こんな感じなんだ。
Kuroshie-san is like this.
なんか、見た目的にはもっとお嬢様清楚おっとり系だと思ったけど、
Somehow, visually I thought she'd be more of a pure, gentle lady type,
意外と俗っぽいな、意外と俗っぽいのだじゃ。
but she's surprisingly common, noja.
話題は振ってくれるけど……ちょっと聞いたことある話が多いな。
She brings up topics, but... many are things I've heard before.
いいだろ別に！
So what! Who cares!
めらお、お前それ望みすぎじゃ！それは望みすぎなのだじゃ！
Merao, you're expecting too much! That's asking too much, noja!
いいじゃろ別に！聞いたことある話しても、
Fine! Even if she talks about something I've heard,
可愛い女の子が話したらなんでも……お前！お前VTuberの配信でも、
if a cute girl talks about it, anything... You! Even on a VTuber's stream,
その話前聞いたとか言うタイプ？許せねえのだじゃ！
are you the type to say "I've heard that before"? I can't forgive that, noja!
めらおが許せねえから帰るのだじゃ！
Since Merao can't forgive it, I'm going home, noja!
のじゃ……ゆゆゆゆ、許してよー！許して欲しいのだじゃー！
Noja... Y-y-y-forgive me! I want you to forgive me, noja!
え、でも知ってる、知ってる話し！さあ、あ、僕もそれ知ってるよとかさ、
Eh, but I know it, I know that story! Come on, ah, I know that too, and like,
ねえ、あ、好感度アップ、1、2、3、4、5、6のだじゃー！
hey, ah, affection up, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, noja!
ふー！よし。
Whew! Okay.
気を使って話題をたくさん出してくれてるのかも。そうじゃよ！そうじゃよ！
Maybe she's going out of her way to bring up lots of topics. That's right!
初めてのデートだよ、デート！一対一だよ！
It's our first date, a date! One-on-one!
クラスメイトと一対一でさ、大して仲良くてなくてさ、デートに行ってさ、話す内容がないんだよ！
One-on-one with a classmate, not particularly close, going on a date, and having nothing to talk about!
めらお、お前と話すことがねえのだじゃ！お前と話すことがねえのに、
Merao, you have nothing to talk about with me, noja! Even though you have nothing to talk about,
クレシエさんはすごい気使って話してくれてるのに、お前望みすぎなのだじゃ！
Kuroe-san is trying so hard to make conversation, you're asking for too much, noja!
うん、そろそろ出よう。
Yeah, let's head out soon.
うわ、あつっ……！
Woah, hot...
いや、令和はね、温度差がね、やばいのじゃ。まだ4月？まだ4月なのに……暑そう。
Man, Reiwa's temperature difference is crazy, you know. Still April? Even though it's still April... looks hot.
最近暑すぎたり、急に寒くなったり、季節感がおかしい気がします。
It's been too hot lately, or suddenly freezing, feels like the seasons are messed up.
いやこれはガチ。これはガチなのだじゃ。
No, this is for real. This is really real, noja.
令和ちゃんがね、あ、これはしま、つなんない、わし、わし、わしがそれなのだじゃ！
Reiwa-chan is... ah, this is boring, I, I, I am that, noja!
令和ちゃんとか言っちゃだめ。うわあ！同じこと考えてるのだじゃ！
Can't say Reiwa-chan. Whoa! Thinking the same thing, noja!
令和にはもっと頑張ってほしいですよね。のだじゃ！わしドールイ？わし、わし、もう冷笑対象？
We want Reiwa to try harder, right? Noja! Am I a doppelganger? Am I already a target of cynical laughter?
わしが悪い？こすられ切ったことしか言えないドールイなのだじゃ！のだじゃ！
Am I bad? I'm a doppelganger who can only say over-scratched things, noja! Noja!
のだじゃ。その話題7回くらいした気がする。いや、毎年のしてるなのだじゃ。
Noja. I feel like I've talked about that topic about 7 times. No, I do it every year, noja.
のだじゃ！わし、わし、もしかしてインターネットでこすられ切った浅い話しかできない系VTuberなのだじゃ？
Noja! Am I, am I by any chance a VTuber who can only talk about shallow topics scraped to death on the internet, noja?
のだじゃ。そんな話をしていると、あっという間に映画館に着いた。
Noja. Talking about stuff like that, we arrived at the cinema in no time.
もう結構ダメージが……もう結構ダメージが……のだじゃ。
Already pretty damaged... already pretty damaged... noja.
ラブコメホラーアクションでしたっけ？映画、楽しみです！
Was it a romantic comedy horror action? I'm looking forward to the movie!
ラブコメホラーアクション見るらしい。結構もりもりなのだじゃ。
She says she watches romantic comedy horror action. Quite a mouthful, noja.
本当にホラー、平気なんだよね？ホラー見るらしい。
You're really okay with horror, right? She says she watches horror.
わしホラーだめ。ねえ、わしホラーだめ。わしホラーだめ。
I hate horror. Hey, I hate horror. I hate horror.
でもめらはいてるらしい。犬猫が死なないかは見ておいた。
But Mera seems to be there. I checked whether dogs and cats die.
確かに行女の子とデートに行って、犬猫が死ぬあの内容だったらわりと空気がね、空気が終わってしまうのだじゃ。
True, if you go on a date with a girl and dogs and cats die in that kind of plot, the mood completely dies, noja.
はい、最近ホラーにハマってるので、任せてください！あ、黒江さんホラーにハマってるらしい。ならよかった。
Yes, I'm into horror lately, so leave it to me! Ah, Kuroe-san is into horror. That's a relief.
他にも映画、色々ありますね。あのポスターとか。いっぱポスターがあるらしい。
There are lots of other movies too. Like that poster. Seems like there are lots of posters.
リバイバル上映だね。昔の映画を劇場でやるみたい。リバイバル上映っていうらしいよ。リバイバル上映多いよね。
It's a revival screening. Seems like they show old movies in theaters. It's called a revival screening. There are a lot of revival screenings, aren't there?
そういうのもあるんですね！あの映画は？平成アニメのリメイクだよ。
There's stuff like that too! What about that movie? It's a remake of a Heisei anime.
リメイク多くね？あの映画は？平成アニメのリボ...同じなのだじゃ。変わらんのだじゃ。
Aren't there a lot of remakes? What about that movie? It's a Heisei anime rebo... It's the same, noja. It doesn't change, noja.
あれは？「昭和名作特撮が復活！」だって。全部同じことなのだじゃ！でもまあ確かに、まあ確かに流行ったものをやるのは王道なのだじゃ！
What's that? "Showa masterpiece tokusatsu is back!" it says. It's all the same thing, noja! But well, certainly, doing what's popular is the royal road, noja!
今って、本当に令和なんですか！？確かにこのラインナップだったらそうなるかも。黒江さんが困惑している。
Is it really Reiwa right now!? True, with this lineup, it might be. Kuroe-san is confused.
上映……。上映後。
Screening... After the screening.
よかったな。なんかのパロっぽいシーン多かったし、あとで解説見よ。わかるー。
That was good. There were a lot of parody-like scenes, I'll check the explanation later. I know, right.
なんか、パロディっぽいシーン多くてもさ、パロディ元がわかんなくてさ、
There were so many parody-like scenes, but I didn't know the sources...
結局なんかそのさ、映画のさ、ハッシュタグとかでさ、あの解説してくれてる人とかをさ、
So in the end, I'd check out people explaining things on movie hashtags and stuff...
見るよね。めっちゃ見るのじゃ。見まくっちゃうのじゃ。
You know? I watch them so much. I watch them endlessly.
栗志江さんはどうかな？
I wonder what Kurishie-san thinks.
面白かったぁ〜！
It was so interesting!
めらおさんはどうでした！？楽しかったですか？
How was it for you, Merao-san? Did you have fun?
あ、うん……自分の感想？そうだね……ええと……映画の感想って言うの難しくない？
Ah, yeah... My thoughts? Well... um... Isn't it hard to give your impressions of a movie?
感想ってけっこう高度な技術な気がしますのじゃ。
Giving impressions feels like a pretty advanced skill, you know.
……それより、栗志江さんの感想が聞きたいな！
...More importantly, I want to hear Kurishie-san's impressions!
わあ、もうどうせ、どうせなんかパロディの話するんでしょ？どうせパロディの話なのじゃ。
Wow, you're just gonna talk about parodies anyway, right? It's all about parodies with you.
はい！怖くて面白かったです！色々あったけど、最後は助かってよかったです！
Yes! It was scary and fun! A lot happened, but I'm glad everyone was saved at the end!
うん。なんか普通、いい、普通のこと。当たり障りないこと。うん。
Yeah. Sort of normal, good, normal things. Harmless things. Yeah.
特に、敵のボスがとっても怖かったですね♡
Especially the enemy boss, she was super scary♡
わ、分かった！ね、マジで何ていうか分かった！ね、マジで何ていうか分かった！どうせ、どうせさ、怖いってさ、
I-I get it! Hey, I seriously get what you mean! Hey, I seriously get it! Anyway, you saying it's scary—
一応見るか。一応見るか。どうせ、どうせ本当に怖いのは、とか言うんじゃろ？
Let me check just in case. Let me check. You're gonna say something like, "Actually, what's truly scary is..." aren't you?
あー、部下を裏切って殺してた人。
Ah, the person who betrayed and killed their subordinate.
この映画、モンスターも怖いけど——どうせさ、本当に怖いのは、人間なのかもしれない、とか言うんじゃろ？
"This movie, monsters are scary, but—" You're gonna say something like, "In the end, the scariest thing might be humans," right?
（怖いけど）。くるぞ！くるぞ！
(Though it's scary). It's coming! It's coming!
本当に怖いのわ、人間なのかもしれませんね……５００回見たのじゃ！５００回見たのじゃ！
"The scariest thing might actually be humans..." I've seen that 500 times! I've seen that 500 times!
確かに、ちょっと気持ちよくなってきた。帰ることもできるけど、ここまで当てられると、ここまで当てられると、ちょっと気持ちよくなってくるのじゃ。
True, it's starting to feel kind of good. I mean, I could just go home, but when you guess it this accurately, it starts to feel kind of satisfying.
なるほど。なるほど。本当に怖いのは、人間なのかも...
I see. I see. "The scariest thing might be humans..."
なんかさ、あのマジネタツィート見るの好きなんじゃけどさ、あのネタツィートでさ、あのよくあるじゃん。なんか「カスの〇〇（これ任意のタイトルが入るじゃん）「カスの〇〇：本当に怖いのは、人間なのかもしれませんね」とか「〇〇は私たちの心の中にいるのかもしれませんね」みたいな
You know, I actually love reading ironic joke tweets, right? Like those joke tweets where it's like, "Scumbag [Title]" — "Scumbag [Title]: The scariest thing might be humans," or "[Title] might be inside our hearts all along," stuff like that!
ネタツィートで５００回見る、あの言われ方ね。ノジア！一手ごわなのじゃ！
That phrasing you see 500 times in meme tweets. So annoying! That's a tough one!
う、うん♡
Y-Yeah♡
それと……知ってますか？映画で「やったか！？」という台詞が出たら、大抵生きてるんですよ？
And... did you know? In movies, whenever someone says, "Did we get him?!", they're almost always still alive?
そうじゃ。「やったか！？」って言ったら大抵生きてるのじゃ。正しいのじゃ。お主は正しいのじゃ。
That's right. When they say "Did we get him?!", they're usually alive. That's correct. You're correct.
ね、可愛くなってきた。なんか可愛いわ。孫を見守る気持ち。なんかインターネット初心者を見守る気持ちなのじゃ。ここまで来ると可愛らしいのじゃ。カエルとかじゃない。可愛いのだ。ドヤ顔でね、「やったか！」「やったか！」はいけないのじゃ。
Man, she's getting cute. She's kind of cute. Like watching over a grandchild. Like watching over an internet beginner. At this point, she's adorable. Not like a frog or anything. She's cute. You shouldn't say "Did we get him?! Did we get him?!" with that smug face.
そ、そうなんだ♡
I-Is that so♡
あ、お腹なった。ご飯、どうする？
Ah, my stomach growled. What do you want to eat?
よ、よければ、このお店にしませんか？
I-If you'd like, would you like to go to this restaurant?
（栗志江さんは、スマホを開いてマップを見せてきた）
(Kurishie-san opened her smartphone and showed her the map.)
カメダ珈琲店か、いいね。
Kameda Coffee Shop, huh? Sounds good.
ねえ、マジわかった！ね、わかった！これ何ていうか、絶対デカすぎっていうのじゃ！もう！
Hey, I seriously get it! Hey, I get it! This is what you'd call—definitely way too huge! Jeez!
はい！では、これから向かいましょう！
Yes! Well then, let's head over!
もう５００回聞いたのじゃ！２名様どうぞ〜
I've heard that 500 times already! Right this way, party of two~
栗志江さん、カメダ好きなの？
Kurishie-san, do you like Kameda?
はい、大好きです！
Yes, I love it!
いいよねー、落ち着くし。
It's nice, very relaxing.
……知ってましたか？カメダ珈琲の料理って、メニューの写真より実物の方が量、すごいんですよ……？
...Did you know? The portions of Kameda Coffee's dishes are actually way bigger in real life than in the menu photos...?
5億回見たのじゃ。
I've seen this 500 million times.
5億回聞いたのじゃ。
I've heard this 500 million times.
逆写真詐欺。逆写真詐欺なのじゃ。
Reverse catfish. It's a total reverse catfish.
そうじゃな。実際デカいよね。
That's right. It's actually huge.
実際デカい。
It's actually huge.
でもなんかきつくないな？思ったよりきつくないな？
But isn't it kind of tight? Not as tight as I thought?
なんかかわいらしい。
Sort of cute.
ネット初心者とともにデートしてる。うん。
Dating a net newbie. Yeah.
かわいいじゃない？
Isn't that cute?
後追い感すごいネット流行の。
It has such a late-to-the-net-trend vibe.
確かに。かなり後追いなのじゃ。
True. It's quite late to the trend.
しかも豆菓子も付いてくるんです……！
Plus, it even comes with bean snacks...!
あれうまいよね。
Those are good, right?
あの豆めっちゃうまいのだ。
Those beans are super good.
わしあの豆めっちゃ好き。
I love those beans so much.
友達がいらないって言ったら強奪する、あの友達がいらないって言ったのもらってね
If a friend says they don't want theirs, I take it... I take the one the friend didn't want
食べる。しょっぱいくてうまいのだ。うん。
and eat it. It's salty and delicious. Yeah.
確かに、魅力的なだよね。
True, it's attractive.
カメダのパンケーキ美味しそう。
Komeda's pancakes look delicious.
菓子メーカーとコラボしてるんだ。
Collaborating with a confectionery maker.
カメダよくコラボしてるよね、お菓子のメーカーとか色んなとこコラボしてるの見るのだ。うん。
Komeda collaborates a lot, doesn't it? I see them collaborating with snack makers and all sorts of places. Yeah.
（あっ）
Ah
終わった！終わったのじゃ！
It's over! It's over!
帰る帰る帰る帰る！
Go back, go back, go back, go back!
くぅ！今日の、今日の朝のデュオリンゴ配信で、今日の朝のデュオリンゴ配信で、
Ugh! In this morning's Duolingo stream, in this morning's Duolingo stream,
あの、コメント欄にホモガキが来て、コメント欄にホモガキが来て、どっち派か聞かれたのだ。どっち派か聞かれまして、
uh, some annoying kids came to the comment section, some annoying kids came to the comment section and asked which side I was on. I was asked which side,
あの、あの炎上が怖すぎて、あえて答えませんでしたのじゃ。
uh, that controversy was too scary, so I purposely didn't answer.
うぬ。ちょっと怖くて、そんな責任わし追えなくて、怖かったから答えなかったのに、
Ugh. I was a bit scared, couldn't take that responsibility, and since I was scared I didn't answer,
クリシエお前、何言うこと配信してんだぞ今！今配信してんだぞわし！
but Kurishie, you—what kind of things are you broadcasting right now?! I'm broadcasting right now!
答えは沈黙！
The answer is silence!
おっ立って、おっ立って、おっ立って！のじゃ！
Calm down, calm down, calm down! Noja!
……めらおさん、来ちゃった。え、これ好感度めっちゃ下がらんない？
......Merao-san, it came. Eh, doesn't this lower favorability a ton?
これ好感度爆下がるのじゃ。いや答えは沈黙ですのじゃ。
This drops favorability massively. No, the answer is silence.
私たち、まだ関係は浅いですが……立場を明確にすることも大切ですよね。
We're still early in our relationship, but... clarifying our positions is also important, right?
終わった……終わったのじゃ……絶対、絶対選択肢で来る……終わったのじゃ……のじゃ……
It's over... It's over... It's definitely, definitely going to come in the choices... It's over... Noja...
その……今後、より親密な関係になるためにめらおさんはどっち派ですか？
For... becoming more intimate in the future, which side are you on, Merao-san?
きのここと、うわ選択肢出てる！
Kinoko and, whoa, the choices are out!
はあ！配信してますのじゃ！配信中なのですのじゃ！
Ha! I'm streaming! I'm in the middle of a stream!
沈黙なし？スキップとか？スキップとか？
No silence? Skip? Skip?
ちょ、いったん帰るか？
W-wait, go back for now?
きのこたけのこ乗りに巻き込まれるのはごめんだよ！
I refuse to get caught up in the Kinoko-Takenoko craze!
ヴー、ヴー。
Buzz, buzz.
あ、母さん、何の用？え……今日だっけ？うん、わかった。
Ah, Mom, what is it? Eh... today? Yeah, got it.
ごめん！家の用事があって帰らないといけなくなった。
Sorry! I had family business and had to go back.
……それは仕方ないですね。今日は お開きにしましょう。うん、ごめんね。
......That can't be helped. Let's call it a day. Yeah, sorry.
(一か八か、口でバイブレーションしたけど何とかばれなかったな。戦略的撤退なのじゃ！撤退なのじゃ！)
(Live or die, I vibrated with my mouth and somehow didn't get caught. It's a strategic retreat! A retreat!)
(やっぱり、昨日は悪いことをした。会ったら嘘ついたの、謝ろう)
(After all, I did a bad thing yesterday. If I see her, I'll apologize for lying.)
あ……クリシエさん！おはよう。
Ah... Kurishie-san! Good morning.
お、おはようございます。
G-Good morning.
えっと、きよ、今日も暑いね。
Uhm, t-today is hot too.
はい！本当に……
Yes! Really...
あ、ちょっと、すみません。うん？
Ah, excuse me for a moment. Hmm?
クリエさん、スマホを操作して何を確認してる？
Kurishie-san, operating your phone, what are you checking?
すみません。やっぱり何でもないです。
Sorry. It's nothing after all.
何か言おうとしてなかった？天気デッキ使おうとしてた？
Weren't you trying to say something? Were you trying to use Weather Deck?
ええ、気にしないでください。
"No, please don't worry about it."
え、何？何、何調べてるの？何調べてるの？
"Eh, what? What are you looking up?"
きっと……自分の言葉が言い尽くされた表現かどうか確認してるんだろう。
"I'm sure she's checking if her words are already overused expressions."
え、切なくて笑った。
"Ah, it's so sad it's funny."
切ないのじゃ。なんか喋れなくなっちゃった。
"It's so sad. I can't talk anymore."
心配なのじゃ。なぜかそうだと、わかった。
"I'm worried. For some reason, I knew it."
自分も似たようなものだからだ。
"It's because I'm similar."
教えてAI！
"Teach me, AI!"
エンディング３なのじゃー！
"Ending 3!"
なんかエンディング切なかったのじゃ。
"The ending was kind of sad."
ええ、なんか、わしが途中で帰っちゃったから？
"Eh, like, because I left midway?"
続きからしたらさ、続きからいけるかな？
"If I start from continue, can I go from continue?"
保存されてるデータがない。いけなっぺい。
"No saved data. Looks like I can't."
ちょっとじゃあ、あの、なんか思ってる切ない系じゃったから、あの、腹をくくってキノコタケノコ戦争に参加するのじゃ。
"So, since it was kind of a sad vibe, I'll steel myself and join the Mushroom vs Bamboo Shoot war."
参加させていただきますのじゃ。セーブ？セーブしなきゃいけないの。
"I will be participating. Save? I need to save."
できそうだった？ちょっと見るか。
"Was that possible? Let me check."
チャプター選択。
"Chapter selection."
あ、いけた！
"Ah, I made it!"
いけたっぽい。
"Seems like it."
よし、２名様どうぞー。
"Alright, table for two, please."
志焉江さん、カメダ好きなの？
"Shizue-san, do you like Kameda?"
はい、大好きです！
"Yes, I love it!"
いいよね、落ち着くし。知ってましたか？
"It's nice, and calming. Did you know?"
カメダ珈琲の料理って、メニューの写真より実物のほうが量、すごいんですよ……？ しかも豆菓子もついてくるんです……！
"At Kameda Coffee, the actual food portions are way bigger than in the menu pictures...? Plus, they even give you bean snacks...!"
確かに、魅力的だよね。カメダのパンケーキ美味しそう。菓子メーカーとコラボしてるんだ。
"True, that's attractive. Kameda's pancakes look delicious. Collaborating with a confectionery maker."
来るぞ！来るぞ！
"It's coming! It's coming!"
わしは、ちょっと炎上はごめんなのじゃ。炎上はごめんなのじゃ。
"I'm sorry, but I'd rather avoid any controversy."
お主ら、お主らいい？
"You guys, you guys good?"
あのね、わしはね、巻き込まれたくない。お主らに任せるのじゃ。うん。
"Well, you see, I don't want to get dragged into this. I'll leave it to you guys. Yeah."
これはね、わしの選択ではない。ミーなのだじゃ。ミーですのだじゃ。
"This isn't my choice. It's mine. It's mine."
これによって、えっと、多数きなのだじゃ！多数きするもののだじゃ！これでわしは燃えない。うん。
"Through this, um, it's majority! Doing majority! With this I won't burn. Yeah."
嫌なのじゃ。なんかタケノコが優勢じゃの。キノコ37、タケノコ63。いっよし。いっよし。
"I hate it. Bamboo shoots seem to have the upper hand. Kinoko 37, Takenoko 63. Alright. Alright."
神回避しゅですのじゃ。
"That's a God dodge."
めらおさん、きちゃった。
"Merao-san, it came."
私たち、まだ関係は浅いですが……立場を明確にすることも大切ですよね。
"We're still early in our relationship, but... making our positions clear is important, right?"
その……今後より親密な関係になるために、めらおさんはどっち派ですか？きのこと、たけのこ……
"Uhm... to become closer in the future, which side are you on, Merao-san? Kinoko or Takenoko..."
はい！コメント欄の、コメント欄の選択なのだじゃ！わしじゃないのだじゃ！わしの選択じゃないよ！
"Yes! The comment section's choice! Not mine! Not my choice!"
ちょ、一応証拠も見せる？一応証拠も見せるか？一応証拠も見せるか？
"Wait, should I show proof just in case? Should I show proof?"
一応証拠も見せるか？証拠ですのじゃ！わしの選択じゃないよ！
"Should I show proof? It's the proof! It's not my choice!"
タケノコが選ばれましたのだじゃ！わしじゃないよ！
"Bamboo shoots were chosen! Not me!"
やはり多数きこそ正義……なのだじゃ！たけのこだよ！
"As expected, majority is justice... is it! It's bamboo shoots!"
がーん！お？クリシエさん、キノコ派か？こ、これからも……お友達でいてくれますか……？
"Gaan! Oh? Krishie-san, a Kinoko fan? W-will you... remain friends with me from now on...?"
めらお、そこまでじゃないよ！縁切るレベルじゃないよ！
"Merao, it's not that far! It's not at the level of cutting ties!"
やばい、クリシエさんタケノコ派だったっぽい。好感度下がっちゃったのだじゃ。
"Oh no, Krishie-san seems to have been a Takenoko fan. My favorability went down."
返らねえのじゃ。さっき帰ったら悲しそうだっただろ。悲しませたくないのだじゃ。
"Can't go back. She looked sad when I left earlier. I don't want to make her sad."
クリシエさん、わかってると思うけど、正直はっきり言うのもあれだけど……きのこたけのこ論争ってごっこ遊びだから本気じゃないよ！
"Krishie-san, I think you know, but to be honest, it's just pretend play, so I'm not being serious!"
そうなんですか？
"Is that so?"
「アレ」を何て呼ぶか、みたいなもんだよ
"It's like what you call 'that thing'."
そうやって配信してるんじゃが、
While streaming like that...
どうする？これでさ、めらおちゃんがこれ派だったからって、
What should we do? Since Merao-chan prefers this one,
ちょっとめらおちゃんちょっと信じられないなみたいななった らどうすんの？どうしてくれるのじゃ？
what if she can't trust Merao-chan anymore? What would you do? How would you make it up to me?
「アレ」を何て呼ぶかみたいなもんだよ。
It's like asking what you call "that thing."
もう任意にするか。任意、任意とさせていただくのじゃ。
Let's just make it optional. Yes, I'll let it be optional.
そう、しかもこれ地方によるし、地域ばれしちゃう！地域ばれの危険がありますのじゃ。ちょっと任意とさせていただきますのじゃ。
Plus, it depends on the region, and it might reveal where you're from! There's a risk of doxxing. So I'll make it optional.
「すみません。それは、何でしようか♡」
"Excuse me. What might that be?"
「丸い生地で中身はあんこの、たい焼きの円盤バージョンみたいなお菓子」
"It's a round pastry with bean paste inside, kind of like a disk version of taiyaki."
「うーん。やっぱり、わからないです♡」
"Hmm. I still don't know."
……薄々思ってたけど、世間知らず？いや、世間知らずっていうか……
...I sort of suspected it, but is she out of touch? No, rather than out of touch...
アイスコーヒー、メロンソーダ、エビカツサンドとフライドチキンセットハムサンドサラダセットです！多くね？二人で食べる量なのじゃ？これが健康的な男女デートの量なのじゃ？多いのじゃ！
Iced coffee, melon soda, shrimp katsu sandwich, fried chicken set, and ham sandwich salad set! Isn't that a lot? Is that enough food for two people? Is this the amount for a healthy boy-girl date? That's way too much!
「わあ……いただきます！」
"Wow... Let's eat!"
栗志江さんはメロンソーダにエビカツサンドフライドチキンセットをもりもり食べていた。ああ、だいぶ食べる。いっぱい食べる、こう可愛い のじゃ。
Kurishie-san heartily ate the melon soda, shrimp katsu sandwich, and fried chicken set. Ah, she eats a lot. She eats a ton, which is so cute.
見た目からは想像できないくらい、健啖家なんだな……
For someone who doesn't look it, she sure has a big appetite...
公園に移動した。カメダでお腹がパンパンになったので、公園に散歩に来た。公園に来たのじゃ。うん。
We moved to the park. Since my stomach was stuffed from Kameda, I came to the park for a walk. I came to the park. Yep.
満腹過ぎて、身体がにぶい。しばらく公園でゆっくりしよう。うん。
I'm too full, my body feels sluggish. Let's relax in the park for a bit. Yeah.
「わあ、魚がたくさん！」
"Wow, so many fish!"
魚がたくさん。カラフルできれいで……カラフル、魚がカラフルなタイプの公園にね、いるのかな？のじゃ。
So many fish. Colorful and pretty... Are they in a park with colorful fish like that?
魚好きなの？今日、水族館でもよかったね。確かに、デートといえばね、水族館みたいなところありますね。
Do you like fish? Today an aquarium would've been nice too. True, when it comes to dates, places like aquariums are classic.
うーん、好きと言えば好きなんですけど……水族館の魚って、見 てるとお腹が減ってきちゃう……
Hmm, I guess I like them, but... fish at the aquarium make me hungry while looking at them...
「おねーさん！コイかいてるからどいて！」
"Hey miss! We're drawing carp, so move!"
でも実際水族館で魚見るとお腹減っちゃうわ言うよね。わしも言いたくなる。わしも言いたくなるのじゃ。
But people really do say that seeing fish at an aquarium makes them hungry. I'd want to say that too. I'd want to say that too.
あ、ごめんね。小学生たちがクーピーで絵を描いている。宿題かな？あ、クーピーでお絵描き。
Ah, sorry. Elementary school kids are drawing pictures with Cray-Pas. Is it homework? Ah, drawing with Cray-Pas.
お絵描き？「うん、オレはカモ、かく！」カモ描いてるのじゃ。
Drawing? "Yeah, I'm drawing a duck!" He's drawing a duck.
「わたしはお花！」
"I'm drawing a flower!"
「あたし、セイレーン～♡」セイレーン？セイレーンいるのじゃ？この子、セイレーンタイプの公園なのじゃ？なるほど？てかクーピーなんだな、クレヨンとかじゃなくて。
"And I'm drawing a Siren~♡" A Siren? There's a Siren? Is this a Siren-type park? I see. Also, they're using Cray-Pas, not crayons or anything.
ねえ！え、かく？かみとクーピーかしてあげる！え、なんか絵をかかせてくれるらしい。絵をかかせてくれるらしい。
"Hey! Want to draw? We'll lend you paper and Cray-Pas!" Eh, apparently they'll let me draw a picture. Apparently they'll let me draw.
めらおが？「かいてかいてー！」
Merao? "Draw, draw!"
何描く？何か「おもしろい」ものかいてよ！ちょ、フリやばくない？
What should I draw? "Draw something 'interesting'!" Wait, isn't that a tough prompt?
最近の、最近のドパパッパたちのフリやばくない？「面白いものかいてよ」だって。え、何がおもろいかな？何がおもろいかな？
Aren't the recent prompts from Dopa-pappa types brutal? "Draw something interesting," they say. Eh, what's interesting? What's interesting?
え……いや、急に言われても
Eh... well, even if you ask me so suddenly...
キューピーン！来たキューピーン！期待されてるね、めっっちゃ期待されてる。
*Ding!* It came! They're expecting a lot from me, they're reeeally expecting a lot.
面白い絵か……まあ、小学生にウケるのは……ムキムキパンのヒーロー、ムキムキ猫型ロボ、あれかな？ホニャえもんをムキムキにしたやつか、フニャパンマンとかをムキムキにしたやつ的なな。ムキムキか……ま、いったんムキムキパンいっとくか。ムキムキにしておくか。うん。
An interesting picture... Well, what appeals to elementary schoolers would be... a buff bread hero, a buff cat-shaped robot, something like that? Or maybe a buff version of Honyaemon, or a buff version of Funyapanman. Buff... Well, let's go with a buff bread hero for now. Let's make it buff. Yeah.
はい描けたよ。まあ子供だからさ、こういうので喜んでくれるでしょ。
There, I drew it. Well, since they're kids, they'll be happy with something like this.
「ありがとー！」わらい、お絵描き、描き終わっちゃった。わっぱ、わっぱ、わらいよ。
"Thank-you!" Haha, drawing, she finished drawing. Wappa, wappa, laughed.
「……えー！国民的キャラクターをマッチョにする落差がおもしろいのは小学生までっしょ！お前ら！お前ら小学生じゃないんか！お前ら！お前ら小学生じゃないんか！」わっぱ！
...Eh! The gap of making a national character buff is only funny to elementary schoolers! You guys! Aren't you elementary schoolers?! You guys! Aren't you elementary schoolers?!" Wappa!
……えー！国民的キャラクターをマッチョにする落差がおもしろいのは小学生までっしょ！
…Eh! Finding the contrast of making a national character buff funny is only for elementary schoolers!
え、せ、せっ生ごろ……
W-Wait, se-segoro...?
な、なん……ま、せ、ませ！ませわっぱすぎんか？ませすぎじゃない？何じゃお前らガチ？
Wh-What... w-wait, wait! Isn't that way too precocious? What are you guys, seriously?
あたしたち、生まれたときからヒカキンとセイキンあびてるもん！どぱーっぱ！
We've been bathed in Hikakin and Seikin since we were born! Dopaa!
どぱわっぱ！
Dopawappa!
のーじゃ……もう……もう……可愛気がないのじゃ……可愛気がないのじゃ……
No... already... already... you have no cuteness... you have no cuteness...
もうだめじゃ、日本終わった……日本終わった……
It's no good anymore, Japan is over... Japan is over...
もう勝てねえ……
I can't win anymore...
ヒカキンさんとセイキンさんの動画に勝てねえよ、マジの上書きじゃ……
I can't win against Hikakin and Seikin's videos, it's a serious overwrite...
いやだな、子供も……こんな笑いじゃもう満足できないよ！
Oh no, even children... can't be satisfied with just laughs like this!
マジか……いやガチマジかだよ。マジかなのじゃ。
Seriously...? No, seriously for real. Seriously.
あれ、栗志江さん？栗志江さんどうした？
Huh, Kurishie-san? Kurishie-san, what's wrong?
……ッ！！ふふ……っ！
...!! Heh... heh...!
ムキキ……ムキムキって……
Buff... buffed up...
おねーさんこんなんでわらってんの！？ちょい、
Big sis, are you laughing at this!? Hold on,
いいじゃん！栗志江さんが笑ってるんだよ、人の笑いを！人の笑いをバカにするんじゃないよ、わっぱ！
that's fine! Kurishie-san is laughing, don't make fun of people's laughter, wappa!
いや良くない！良くないのじゃ！ちょ、もうちょい道徳を学ぶのじゃお姉ら！
No, that's not good! Hold on, learn a bit more about morals, you guys!
これで！？あっさー！ちょ、メスわっぱなのはじゃ。何言っとるん？
With this!? Asaa! Hold on, you're a female wappa. What are you saying?
「いっしゅめ」じゃん！おねーさんやばいー！
"First round" my foot! Big sis is crazy!
そんな一言言うなよ、お前！「いっしゅめ」って……ませてんねえ！
Don't say such a single word, you! Saying "first round"... you're precocious!
ませてんねえ！「いっしゅめ」って……いいじゃろ！おもしろいものは面白いでいいじゃろ！
You're precocious! Saying "first round"... that's fine! If something's funny, it's fine!
失礼な！散れ散れ！本当だよ失礼な！わっぱ！
Rude! Scatter, scatter! Seriously, that's rude! Wappa!
は～い。が、こういうさ、言葉遣いどこで覚えてくるの？どこで覚えてくるのこういう言葉遣い？
Heeey. But where do you learn this kind of phrasing? Where do you learn this kind of phrasing?
誰が教えた？YouTubeか？お前らYouTubeでこういうこと……誰かが「いっしゅめ」とか人を笑っていたらさ！
Who taught you? YouTube? You guys on YouTube... if someone is laughing at people with "first round"!
良くない物を摂取しておりますのじゃ。父ちゃんメラの配信を見て優しい心を学ぶのじゃ。
You are consuming bad things. Learn a kind heart by watching father Mela's stream.
……スーー……はあ……はあ……ごめんなさい。変ですよね。
...Suu... hah... hah... I'm sorry. It's weird, isn't it?
まあ、急にツボに入るってよくあることだよ。
Well, suddenly getting tickled by something happens all the time.
いいえ、それだけじゃなくて……今日一日……私、変だったでしょう。
No, not just that... All day today... I've been weird, haven't I?
変？そうかな。
Weird? I wonder.
めらおさん……ごめんなさい。今日、私のお話にここまで付き合って下さって……
Merao-san... I'm sorry. Thank you for keeping me company with my talk today...
私のお話……きっと、あまり楽しくないから。これ以上お付き合いいただくのも、悪いです。
My talk... surely isn't very fun. So it's bad of me to keep taking up your time.
ねえ、さっきのさ、ドパワッパ達がさあ！ひどいこと言ったせいでモカちゃん傷ついちゃってるのじゃ！
Hey, because those dopawappa earlier said terrible things, Moka-chan got hurt!
モカちゃんが……へこんじゃってるよ！ねえ！がち……何？何傷つけてるん、ひとを。
Moka-chan is... feeling down! Hey! Seriously... what? What are you hurting people for?
もしよければ、ここで解散にしませんか？
If you'd like, why don't we break up here?
帰らない！絶対帰んないのじゃ！ちょ、ここまで言われたら女の子が悲しんでる！女の子が悲しんでる！帰らない！
I won't go home! Absolutely not going home! Wait, when she's said this much, the girl is sad! The girl is sad! I won't go home!
栗志江さん……は、はいっ。ベンチで休まない？いいですけど……
Kurishie-san... Y-Yes. Won't you rest on a bench? I don't mind, but...
めらお……栗志江さんって、中学までどんな感じだったの？栗志江さんって、中学までどんな感じだったの？
Merao... Kurishie-san, what were you like until middle school? Kurishie-san, what were you like until middle school?
両親の都合で、今年３月まで欧州にいました。小中は全寮制の女子校でしたね。
Due to my parents' circumstances, I was in Europe until March of this year. Elementary and middle school were full-board girls' schools.
確かに。この経歴ならね、全寮制の女子校にいたら確かに、ぞくっぽい
True. With this background, if you were in a full-board girls' school, you definitely
インターネットに触れることない、隔離されてるから……知らないよねえ？
wouldn't have contact with sketchy internet because you're isolated... so you don't know, right?
知らないよねえ？そうじゃったらもう全部新鮮だよねえ？
You don't know, right? If so, then everything is fresh to you, right?
じゃあもう、しゃあないじゃん！笑うなよ！笑うなよこの子のこと！
Well then, it can't be helped! Don't laugh! Don't laugh at this girl!
帰国子女なのだ。わしも、わしも、わしも、わしも
A returnee student... Me too, me too, me too, me too!
和菓子にピンと来てなかったのはそういう訳か。ああ、あの任意のね。
So that's why you didn't get Japanese sweets. Ah, that optional one, right?
任意の、あんこの入った、あのまるいお菓子ね。確かに、確かに。
That optional, round sweet with red bean paste. True, true.
前は、校則が厳しくて、TVもスマホも禁止。娯楽はドラえもんとかアンパンマンの本だけでした♥
Before, school rules were strict, and phones were banned. Entertainment was just Doraemon and Anpanman books.
でも今年、日本に帰ることになったので父を説得して公立高校に進学したんです♥
But since we're returning to Japan this year, I persuaded my father and entered public high school.
なるほど。
I see.
やっと、やっと日本の子供らしい人間の生活ができるようになったんじゃ？
Finally, I can live a normal Japanese childhood human life, right?
できるようになったのに！
Even though I'm able to now!
時代遅れの流生…流生…されちゃってるんじゃ！
It's already outdated!
ひどいのだじゃ！ひどいのだじゃ！世界って！
It's terrible! This world is terrible!
へえ。スマホは持ってたよね。それも解禁されたの？
Hee, you had a smartphone. Was that also unlocked?
はい！私、普通の学生生活が送れるようになったんです！
Yes! I'm able to live a normal student life now!
いい話じゃん！
What a nice story!
つまんないとか言ってごめん！浅いとか言ってごめん！一周目とか言ってごめん！
Sorry for calling it boring! Sorry for calling it shallow! Sorry for calling it a first run!
やっぱ誰にでもあんだからね、初めてってね！
After all, everyone has a first time!
その初めての楽しさを笑うことなんてね、しちゃいけないのじゃ！
You shouldn't laugh at that first-time joy!
それで春休みは行きたいお店とイベントに全部行って、映画とドラマ三昧で……！
And during spring break, I went to all the shops and events, and binged movies and dramas...
この春休みは、初めて知ることがたくさんありました！
This spring break, I learned so many new things for the first time!
いい話じゃん！
What a nice story!
「かき氷シロップはどれも味は同じ」とか……
"All shaved ice syrups taste the same"...
「結婚の予定がある新兵は死ぬ」とか……
"A rookie with wedding plans is doomed"...
まあ、まあそう。まあそう。
Well, well, yeah. Well, yeah.
実際かき氷のシロップって本当に同じなのだろうか？
Do shaved ice syrups really all taste the same?
言うけどね。
Or so they say.
毎日新しい発見があって、楽しかった。
Every day brought new discoveries, it was fun.
ご学友の皆さんとも共有したかった。
I wanted to share it with my school friends too.
そうだよね、発見ってね！発見って共有したいよね！
That's right, discoveries! You want to share discoveries!
でも……
But...
でも？
But?
新しい発見、だと思ってたのは、私だけだったんです……。
I thought it was a new discovery... but I was the only one...
切ないのじゃ……。
How heartbreaking...
まあ、誰か日本で過ごしてね、子供の頃からYouTube見てたらね、触れてるよね。
Well, if anyone lived in Japan and watched YouTube since childhood, they'd know.
そういえば先週、隣の席で女子3人が何か言ってたな……
Come to think of it, last week three girls at the next desk were saying something...
いじわるなこと言ったんでしょ！
They must have said something mean!
女子3人いじわるなこと言った？言ったんだろ！
Did three girls say something mean? They must have!
栗志江さん、どう？
Kurishie-san, how is it?
ん……悪い子じゃないけど……つまんないかも。
Hmm... she's not a bad girl, but... maybe boring.
それ！知ってる話しかないよね！
That! She only talks about things we already know!
ちょ厳しくない？笑いに厳しくないか？女子！
Isn't that harsh? Isn't she harsh on comedy, girls?
この前も「スマホの充電1%は意外と持つ！」って言っててさー
Just the other day she said, "Phone battery at 1% lasts surprisingly long!"
やば笑
No way, lol.
それショートで流れてきたら飛ばすわ～
If that comes up on Shorts, I'd skip it~
のじゃ！はい！はい！阿智めらに500のダメージ！
Noja! Yes! Yes! 500 damage to Achi Melani!
えーなんかやっぱ動画とか見ながらこういうこと思われてるのかなあ……
Man, I wonder if people think this while watching videos...
ショートで流れてきたら飛ばすわとか思われてるのじゃ……
Thinking "I'd skip it if it came up on Shorts"...
はいダメージ！
Damage!
ダメージなのだじゃVTuber阿智めらに500のダメージ！
VTuber Achi Melani takes 500 damage!
のじゃ！ちょ、これガチ言われたら泣く。大泣きなのだじゃ。
Noja! Man, if someone said this for real, I'd cry. I'd cry my eyes out.
……栗志江さんをそう評価する生徒もいた。
......Some students evaluated Kurishie-san like that.
うちのクラス、あるあるの頻度にやたら厳しい人が多いし……
In our class, there are so many people who are super strict about clichés...
私の発見は……面白くともなんともなかった。
My discovery... wasn't interesting at all.
でさ、こういうさ、あるある系をさ、なんかYouTubeショートでさ、知るとかじゃなくてさ、自分で発見してるのすごくよ！
And discovering cliché things like this yourself on YouTube Shorts rather than just hearing about it is amazing!
自分がいぶかった……周回遅れなんだって、最近やっと気づきました。
I was slow... I finally realized lately that I'm a lap behind.
そんな周回遅れとか寂しいこと言わないでよ！
Don't say sad things like being a lap behind!
それなのに自分が初めて見つけたようにはしゃいで、披露して……いいのじゃ別に！
Even so, getting excited and showing it off as if you found it for the first time... It's fine, whatever!
今日も、ご友人と遊ぶなんて滅多になくて、気持ちが高ぶってしまいました。
Today, I rarely get to hang out with friends, so my emotions ran high.
ごめんね、帰るボタン押して。ごめんね、帰るボタン押して。
Sorry, I pressed the return button. Sorry, I pressed the return button.
今日も、ご学友と遊ぶなんて滅多になくて、
Today, hanging out with schoolmates is so rare,
気持ちが昂ってしまいました。
I got so excited.
それで……手垢のついた、つまらないことばかり言ってしまった。
And so... I ended up saying all these cliché, boring things.
栗志江さん……
Kurishie-san...
漏れもそうだよ！
Me too!
漏れもだよ！
わしも自分のことを一二称漏れだけど、大丈夫なのだろうじゃ？
I use first-person "more" for myself too, but is that okay?
わしもわしも一二称漏れなのだろうじゃ？終わってるのだろうじゃ？終わってるインターネット、ドパウッパぺすのじゃ？大丈夫なのだろうじゃ？
Am I also a first-person "more" user? Is it over? Is it a totally ruined internet? Is that okay?
自分も、そういうことあったよ。
I've had things like that happen too.
え？めらおさんが？
Eh? Merao-san?
子供の時、セミは地面に落ちてても急に鳴くやつもいるって気づいたんだ。
When I was a kid, I noticed that even cicadas on the ground sometimes suddenly start crying out.
確かに。あれ怖いよね。
True. That's scary, right?
当時は大発見だと思った。でも友達に「知ってる」って笑われてさ。
At the time I thought it was a huge discovery. But my friends laughed and said, "I know."
悲しいのじゃ……そう、セミファイナル！セミファイナルのことなのじゃ。
So sad... That's right, the semifinal! It's about the semifinal!
悔しくて……「〇〇あるある」系のショートをひたすら見て勉強した。
Feeling frustrated... I studied by endlessly watching "XX common sense" shorts.
サラマンダーあるあるも見てもおじのじゃ！ね、サラマンダーあるあるのショートも見て……
I watched salamander common sense too! Hey, I also watched salamander common sense shorts...
それは、熱心ですね。
That's quite enthusiastic.
最初は楽しいけど、何個も見ているとよく語られるネタがわかってきて、「このネタ、流行ってるやつの真似じゃん」みたいなのも見えてきて……
At first it's fun, but watching a lot of them, you start to understand common tropes, seeing things like, "This joke is just copying whatever's trending..."
ねえ、そういうこと言うの、めらお、お前はユーチューバーになれ！めらお、お前はユーチューバーになるのじゃ！なんかね、もうつまんないなとか流行ってるやつの真似じゃんとか、そういうのがわかってきたら
Hey, saying stuff like that—Merao, you should become a YouTuber! Merao, you're gonna be a YouTuber! You know, once you realize things like "this is boring" or "it's just a copy of what's popular,"
お主が動画を出すフェーズなのじゃ。もう視聴者のフェーズにいないのじゃ、お話は。もうお主は十分発信者側の資格があるのじゃ！動画を作るのじゃ！のじゃ！
You've reached the phase where you should put out videos. You're no longer in the viewer phase. You already have plenty of qualifications as a creator! You're gonna make videos!
そのうちネットじゃ何を見ても、既視感しかなくなってきて……お主が動画を作るのじゃ！
Soon, no matter what you see on the internet, you'll only feel déjà vu... You're the one who will make videos!
めらおさん……？
Merao-san...?
おかげで使い古された表現には詳しくなったけど、今度は怖くなった。
Thanks to that, I became well-versed in worn-out expressions, but now I've gotten scared.
自分の言った感想や意見が、手垢のついた話だったらどうしようって。
What if the impressions and opinions I express are just cliché stories?
それは周りがいじわる過ぎなのだろうじゃ！それは周りがいじわる過ぎなのだろうじゃ！
That's just because people around you are too mean! That's because people around you are too mean!
いいじゃん別に、あるある言ったってね！
It's fine to say common things, right!
それで、映画の感想も、明確には言ってくれなかったんですね。
And so, you didn't state your impressions of the movie clearly either, did you?
確かに。めらお映画の感想つきって言ってなかったな。うん。
True. Merao didn't say she gave her impressions with the movie. Yeah.
だから……栗志江さんにはめらおみたいに気にし過ぎないでほしいんだ。
That's why... I don't want Kurishie-san to worry too much like Merao does.
確かに。確かにもう誰かが見つけたことかもしれない。けど、栗志江さんが自分で発見したんでしょ？
True. Someone else might have already found it. But Kurishie-san discovered it herself, right?
それは「つまらないこと」なんかじゃないよ！
That is by no means a "boring thing"!
……お気遣い、ありがとうございます。そう言っていただけるだけでも、嬉しいです。
...Thank you for your consideration. Just hearing you say that makes me happy.
気を使わせてるのは、こっちだ。お似合いなんじゃないめらおと。
The one making you walk on eggshells is me. Aren't you and Merao a good match?
こんな……それこそ、どこかで聞いたような慰めの言葉じゃ届かない。
Words of comfort like this... heard somewhere before, won't reach me.
……昔からそうだ。他人と被ることにびくびくしてたけど、結局ラクだから、他人と同じようなことをして……
...It's been like that since long ago. I was terrified of overlapping with others, but in the end, since it's easy, I ended up doing the same things as others...
ああ、もう！
Ah, jeez!
ごめん、ちょっと待ってて！めらおどっか行っちゃった。え、お似合いなのじゃ？いいカップル？
Sorry, wait a second! Merao went somewhere. Eh, a good match? A good couple?
へっ？
Huh?
うん？どうした？めらおどうした？
Hmm? What's wrong? What's wrong, Merao?
あ、かき氷！公園の入り口にあった、屋台の？
Ah, shaved ice! The one at the park entrance, at the food stall?
うん。あの屋台は年中かき氷を売ってる狂った店だから……狂った店来た！狂った店来た狂った店！
Yeah. That stall is a crazy shop that sells shaved ice all year round... A crazy shop appeared! A crazy shop is here, a crazy shop!
どうして急に？
Why all of a sudden?
かき氷のシロップはどれも同じ味だってのは、知ってる……知ってるつもりだった。
That all shaved ice syrups taste the same is something I knew... or at least thought I knew.
でも、それは漫画とかネットで見て知った気になってるだけなんだ。確かに、実際食べ比べしたことないのじゃ。
But that was just feeling like I knew it from manga and the internet. Truly, I've never actually compared them, you see.
本当に味が同じなのか、自分で確認したことはない。
I've never checked for myself whether they really taste the same.
だから今、試す！男の子なのじゃ！わ、かなり、かなりあのラブラブめろめろ、いい感じの……なんだっけ？くっついちゃうよ！
That's why I'm testing it right now! I'm a boy! Wow, quite... quite that love-love melt-melt, good vibe... what was it? We're gonna stick together!
あああっ！そんなペースで……！すごいペースで食べてる！めらお、めらおをやばいペースで食べてるのじゃ！
Aaah! At that pace...! Eating at an amazing pace! Merao is eating Merao at a dangerous pace!
ど、どうですか？
H-How is it?
いや、舌が冷えてわからなくなってきた。ヒヤックなのだじゃ！ヒヤックなのだじゃ！
No, my tongue has gotten cold and I can't tell anymore. It's icy! It's icy!
ううっ、寒い！歯がいたい！
Ugh, cold! My teeth hurt!
なーお
Nao.
大変！上着あるので着てください
Oh no! I have a jacket, please put it on.
ありがとう、栗江江さん
Thank you, Kurie-san.
いい空気じゃないの！いい空気なのじゃ！
What nice air! It's such nice air!
ラブラブ男女ですのじゃ。こういう人間が付き合うんじゃろ？
They're a lovey-dovey couple. People like this date, right?
私も、何度か違う味のかき氷を食べるうちに違和感を覚えたので、食べ比べをしたんですが……
I also felt something was off while eating shaved ice of different flavors, so I compared them...
ちゃんとゆっくり、温かいお茶を飲みながらやったんですから、早食いはダメですよ！
I did it slowly while drinking warm tea, so eating fast is no good!
自力で気づくのもすごいし、食べ比べて検証するのもすごいな……
Realizing it on your own is amazing, and comparing and verifying is also amazing...
栗江江さん、全然浅くもつまらなくもないよ。むしろすごいよ……
Kurie-san, it's neither shallow nor boring at all. It's actually amazing...
えー、好意の予感。そ、そうですか？
Eh, a hint of affection. I-is that so?
うん！……ああ、くち冷たい。台無しなのじゃ
Yeah! ...Ah, my mouth is cold. It's ruined.
めらおは、大きく口を開けて、冷気を口から逃がそうとした
Nao opened her mouth wide, trying to let the cold air escape.
ふ、ふふ……っ
Hehe...!
え？
Eh?
ごめんなさい！でも……あははっ！めらおさん、舌が緑！
I'm sorry! But... hahaha! Nao-san, your tongue is green!
おーー、いい空気ですのじゃ！あははは……っ
Ooh, what nice air! Ahahaha...!
（かき氷のメロン味で舌の色が……またベタなことしちゃったな。まあ、でも……初めて栗江江さんの満面の笑みが見れたし、いっか……）
((My tongue is the color of melon shaved ice... I did a cliché thing again. Oh well, but... I got to see Kurie-san's full smile for the first time, so it's fine...))
いい話……いい話。チューはしてないのじゃ？そういうのは早いのじゃ？
A good story... A good story. Didn't they kiss? Is that too soon?
今日だるかったー！早く帰ろー
Today was so sluggish! Let's go home early.
今日は何もないし、帰ろっかな
There's nothing going on today, I guess I'll go home.
お疲れ様です。栗江江さん！
Good work. Kurie-san!
（あの日以降、めらおは、前よりも栗江江さんと話すようになっていた）
((Ever since that day, Nao had been talking to Kurie-san more than before.))
その、これから予定ありますか？部活とか、塾とか……え、なんかすっごい仲良し！すっごい仲良しなのだじゃ！まだ付き合ってないの？
Um, do you have any plans after this? Club activities, cram school... Eh, you're super close! You're super close! Aren't you dating yet?
ううん。ないよ
N-no. I don't.
あ……あの……よ、よかったら……タピオカ屋さんに行きませんか！あー、やっぱね、流行ってる、流行ってたやつね、回収したいよね？
Ah... um... i-if you'd like... would you like to go to a tapioca shop! Ah, right, you want to reclaim that trending, trendy thing, right?
デートのお誘いなのじゃ
It's an invitation to a date.
タピオカ？
Tapioca?
はい。私、一人で行った経験はあるのですが……友達と行ったことないって言ったら、友達いないで……あれかな、悲しくさせちゃおうかな
Yes. I have experience going alone, but... if I say I've never gone with a friend, then... I have no friends... I wonder if that would make them sad.
クラスメイトと行ったことないから、とか？
Like, 'Because I've never gone with a classmate'?
クラスメイト……じゃなくて！友達と行きたいんです！も、漏れでっか？わしなのだじゃ！
Classmate... no! I want to go with a friend! M-moredecca? Washi na no ja!
うん、もちろん！だけど……友達ならもうちょっと砕けた感じでもいいんじゃない？
Yeah, of course! But... if you're friends, wouldn't it be better to be a bit more casual?
あ……口調、ですか？すみません。この喋り方、癖でさ
Ah... tone, you say? I'm sorry. This way of speaking is a habit.
でも……そうですね。一緒に行こう、めらお！――えー、なんがいい空気！いい空気なのだじゃ！
But... that's right. Let's go together, Nao! ——Ee, what nice air! It's such nice air!
てあカノ。手垢のついたことしか言わない彼女
[Title: Teakano - A Girlfriend Who Only Says Cliché Things]
ED5『ひとりじゃわからないこと』
[ED5: Things You Can't Understand Alone]
いい話なのだじゃー！いい話なのだじゃ！
Such a good story! Such a good story!
エンディング5、回収しましたのだじゃ
I've collected Ending 5.
じゃあ、他のエンディングも回収していくか。他のエンディングも回収していくまなのだじゃ
Well then, I'll go collect the other endings too. I'll collect the other endings too.
帰るタイミングによって変わるらしいから
It seems to change depending on when you go home.
いったん、この一番最初の栗江江モカさんのインフルるの時の夢で帰ろう
For now, let's go home with Kurie Moka-san's dream from when she had influenza at the very beginning.
インフルるの時の夢で帰ろう
Let's go home with the dream from when she had influenza.
電車遅れてた？よしよしよしよしよしよし！すぐ帰宅する
Was the train delayed? Good, good, good, good! I'll head right home.
なんというかまるでインフルエンザの時の夢みたいですね……すぐ帰宅したく感じ悪くない？
It's like a dream when you have influenza... Doesn't it feel bad to want to go home right away?
でもまあ、回収のためじゃからな。右上に帰るボタンがあり……インフルエンザの時の夢。帰たくあ
Well, it's for collection. There's a 'Go Home' button at the top right... A dream during influenza. Want to go ho—
え、せ……しんれつ……
Uh, se... shinretsu...
しんれつのじゃ！
Shinretsu!
今時インフルエンザの時の夢って面白いと思ってるのかな
Do they really think dreams during the flu are funny nowadays?
急激に帰りたくなってきた。適当に理由つけよう。
I suddenly want to go home. I'll make up some excuse.
めらお、やだなやつ！めらお、ガチやだなやつ！
Merao, what an annoying guy! Merao is seriously annoying!
あ、ごめん！！今日用事あったんだって！来るな！最初から言え！
Ah, sorry!! I had plans today! Don't come! Say so from the start!
栗志江さんごめん！帰らないと！
Kurishie-san, sorry! I have to go home!
まあ、そうなんですか？映画のチケット代は……
Oh, is that so? The movie ticket price...
自分がい悪いし、お金いらないよ。よかったら観てきて！
It's my fault, you don't need money. Go watch it if you like!
じゃあ！
See ya!
やだなやつ……え、なんか苦しい、切なくなってきたのじゃ。
What an annoying guy... Ugh, it feels painful and depressing.
辛い……うーん。
It hurts... Sigh.
もっか……
Once more...
最低なのじゃ。
How awful.
どうだった？日曜に栗志江さんと遊んだんでしょ？うん、まあ。
How was it? You hung out with Kurishie-san on Sunday, right? Yeah, well.
栗志江さんと！？何話したんだよ、めらお！いや、そんなに……
With Kurishie-san!? What did you talk about, Merao! No, not really...
なんだよそれ！栗志江さんは何か言ってた？
What's that supposed to mean?! Did Kurishie-san say anything?
駅のオブジェを「インフルの時の見る夢」に例えてた。
She compared the station's object to "dreams you see when you have the flu".
あ……ねえ、このタイミングで……
Ah... Hey, if she comes in at this timing...
栗志江さん入ってきたらどうするのじゃ！栗志江さんってそういうところあるよね。
What would you do if Kurishie-san walked in?! Kurishie-san can be like that.
「今それ？」みたいな話を面白い感じで言ってくるの。「行けたら行く」は結局来ないとか、「2日目のカレーの方が美味しい」とか……
She casually drops lines like "Is that relevant now?". Like "I'll go if I can" meaning she never shows up, or "Curry is better on the second day"...
え、何それ？やばっ、一周すぎるっしょ！
Eh, what's that? Whoa, that's way off!
いくら顔が良くても、つまんねー女は性格悪いとかより……そんなことないのじゃ！つまんない！性格悪い女が嫌なのじゃ！
No matter how good-looking she is, a boring woman is worse than having a bad personality... That's not true! It's boring! I hate women with bad personalities!
今時ネットとか賞レースで一般人も笑いのリテラシーが上がってるんだからさ、もう少し何というか……
Nowadays, with the internet and comedy awards, ordinary people's comedy literacy has gone up, so you know, a bit more...
お、栗志江さん入ってきたじゃん！絶対入ってきたじゃん！
Oh, Kurishie-san came in! She definitely came in!
あ……おはよう、栗志江さん。ねえ、やなクラス通いたいっないのじゃ！転校するのじゃ！
Ah... Good morning, Kurishie-san. Hey, I don't want to go to this annoying class! I'm transferring!
……おはようございます。
...Good morning.
(栗志江さんは挨拶をすると、足早に離れていった)
Kurishie-san greeted him and quickly walked away.
(それが、栗志江さんとまともに会話した最後の機会だった……)
That was the last time I had a proper conversation with Kurishie-san...
ねえ、やだなクラス！登校を拒否するのじゃ！行かないのじゃ！こんな学校行かないのじゃ！
Hey, what an annoying class! I refuse to go to school! I won't go! I won't go to a school like this!
エンディング1、疎遠。
Ending 1: Estranged.
切ないのじゃ……
How depressing...
子どもって悪気なくこういうこと言うよね。でもそれって悪意なのじゃ。やな学校、心が痛いのじゃ。
Kids say things like this without malice. But that is malice. What an annoying school, my heart hurts.
もう帰りたくなってきた。もう帰りたくない。次は映画館で帰らなきゃいけないのじゃ。
I already want to go home. I don't want to go home anymore. Next I have to go home from the movie theater.
苦しいのじゃ……映画楽しみです！のじゃ。のじゃ。
It's painful... I'm looking forward to the movie! ...nodja.
ああ、こんなイイ子なのに、こんなイイ子なのに帰らなきゃいけない。こんなイイ子なのに……疑問？
Ah, such a good girl, yet I have to go home even though she's such a good girl. Such a good girl... Question?
「全米が泣いた」という宣伝文句、本当だと思いますか……？そうだよね、全米が泣いたって本当に泣いたかわからないよね。わしだって、あの唐揚げの金賞って本当に全部の唐揚げが唐揚げの金賞になってるなって思うのじゃ。
Do you think the promotional tagline "America wept" is true...? That's right, you don't know if all of America actually wept. Even I wonder if all karaage that win gold awards really deserve to be karaage gold medalists.
観客の皆さんが泣いているか、全てチェックするのは無理ですよね。確かに。栗志江さん、真剣だ。
It's impossible to check if every single audience member is crying, right? True. Kurishie-san is so serious.
よかったな。何かのパロっぽいシーン多かったし、あとで解説見よう。最初に帰るルートをかいじゅうすればよかった！
That's good. There were a lot of parody-like scenes, I should check the explanations later. I should have just taken the route to go home first!
最初に帰ればよかった！いた……いたたたた……
I should have gone home first! Ouch... ouch ouch ouch...
大丈夫ですか？いや、お腹が……あーーい、これマジで、やばいマジで……下痢病なのじゃ！
Are you okay? No, my stomach is... aaah, i-, this is seriously, dangerously serious... I have diarrhea!
大変……！無理せず、今日は帰りましょう。うん、本当にごめんね。チケット代はいらないから。それじゃあ……はい、お気をつけて……
Oh no...! Don't push yourself, let's go home today. Yeah, I'm really sorry. You don't need to pay for the ticket. Well then... Yes, take care...
ああ、順番間違えたのじゃ！
Ah, I got the order wrong!
おはよう。おはよう。
Good morning. Good morning.
あ、栗志江さん。クラスの他の女子と話しているようだ。
Ah, Kurishie-san. It looks like she's talking to other girls in the class.
それでね、まあ……そうなんですね。そうなの、でさー。
And so, well... Is that so? That's right, soー.
うふふ、そうなんですね。あれ？栗志江さん……全然自分の話してないな。
Hehehe, is that so? Huh? Kurishie-san... isn't talking about herself at all.
あの日以来、栗志江さんは会話の時、いつも微笑んで相手を肯定していた。うわ、社会性を覚えちゃったんだ！
Ever since that day, Kurishie-san always smiled and agreed with people during conversations. Wow, she learned social skills!
社会性を覚えちゃって……やだなのじゃ！
She learned social skills... How annoying!
自分の思ってる事が素直に言える環境がなくなっちゃったのじゃ。
...that environment has disappeared, hasn't it?
（しかし、自分から話を切り出したり、周りと違う意見を言うことは二度となかった……）
However, she never again spoke her mind or differed from others...
ED2「栗志江さんは語らない」。切ないのじゃ……！
Ending 2: "Kurishi-e Doesn't Speak." What a bittersweet ending!
うわ、なんかノベルゲー初めてやっちゃったからさ！
Wait, this is my first time getting a visual novel's ending!
わしさ、ノベルゲーやったことなかったからさ、お作法を知らなかったけどさ、
I've never played a visual novel before, so I didn't know about bad ends, but...
もしかしてさ、こういうノベルゲーってさ、バッドエンドを最初に回収して、いいエンドにすべきだったの？
could it be that for these games, you're supposed to get the bad end first, and then the good end?
うわー、知らなかったー！知らなかったのじゃ！
Oh, I didn't know! I really didn't know!
じゃあ、エンディング4もみるか。切ないのじゃ。
Let's check Ending 4 as well... That's so sad.
うーん、辛いのじゃ。
How painful.
公園に来ましたのじゃ。
I came to the park for a walk.
魚なのかな？
Fish?
今日、水族館でもよかったね♥
We should've gone to the aquarium instead, huh?
（小学生たちがクーピーで絵を描いてる。宿題かな）
The kids are saying, "Hey, mister! There are carp over there, so move!"
うん。オレはカモ、かく！♥
"Yeah, I'm drawing a duck!"
あたし、セイレーン♥
"I'm a siren!"
へえー♥
"Heh."
ねえ！え、かく？かみとクーピーかせる！♥
"Draw me a duck too!"
かいてかいてー！何か「おもしろい」ものかいてよ！♥
"Draw! Draw something interesting for us!"
いや、急に言われても♥
Hey, don't ask for that so suddenly!
期待されてる～～♥期待されてる！
They're expecting so much from me!
えーっと、ムキムキ猫型ロボ。
Uh, a muscular cat robot.
ありがとー！♥
"Thank you!"
……えー！国民的キャラクターをマッチョにする落差がおもしろいのは小学生までっしょ！♥
"No way! Making a national character buff like that isn't funny to elementary schoolers at all!"
あれ！？♥
What?!
マジか……♥のじゃ。
Seriously?!
笑ってるーー！栗志江さん笑ってくれてありがとうーー！
She's laughing! Kurishi-e is laughing, thank you!
おねーさんこんなんでわらってんの！？♥
"Miss, you're laughing at this?! Caller: Hey, don't say that!"
のじゃ。お笑いしてる。
She's cracking up!
のじゃ。ごめんなさい。え……？♥
Ah...
私の お話……きっと、あまり楽しくないから。これ以上付き合っていただくのも、悪いです♥
"Ah, isn't it painful to go home after this?"
この流れで帰れなくない？この流れで帰る選択肢にするの？無理ですのじゃあーー！
"Wouldn't it be better to just part ways right here?"
帰るけど、ひどいのじゃあ。
I'm going home, but it's so miserable.
……めらおは帰った。
Merao went home.
人の心とか……ないんか。
Does she have a heart or not?
栗志江さんは変わらない笑顔で、手を振っていた。
Kurishi-e waved goodbye with the same smile as always.
化け物なのか。サラマンダーをもうちょい、もうちょい心はあるのじゃ。
Is she a monster? Does she actually have a heart somewhere?
おはよー。おはよう。
"Morning."
栗志江さん、いないな。いつも早いのいに。
"Kurishi-e isn't here. She's usually early."
栗志江さんは休みだって♥
"Kurishi-e is taking the day off."
そうか……うわ、絶対めらおのせいじゃーー！
"Is that so..." No way, this has got to be my fault!
そうかじゃねえよ。女の子心線かんな？
No, it's not. Girls don't shut down that easily.
次の日――先生
The next day—
栗志江は、今日も体調不良で欠席だそうだ♥
"Kurishi-e is absent today due to feeling unwell."
ねえっ、めらおーー！
No way, Merao...
なんか途中まで心開いてさ、いけるよかん出してさ、やっぱ無理って拒絶するのが一番よくないのじゃ。
Man, opening up halfway and then trying to push through...
栗志江は今日も欠席か。誰か家、近いやついるか？
"Kurishi-e is absent again today. Anyone live close to her?"
（………………）♥
(Silence...)
（次の日、栗志江さんは学校に来た）♥次...
The next day, Kurishi-e came to school.
みんな心配していたし、栗志江さんも穏やかにそれに答えていた）
Everyone was worried, and Kurishi-e answered them calmly.
（ただ……それからの栗志江さんは、あの日の溌剌さを、永久に失っていた）ねえ、何しとんの！
However, ever since that day, Kurishi-e had lost that spark forever...
子どもにバカにされた後、栗志江さんは目に見えて落ち込んでいたじゃないか。
After being made fun of by the kids, Kurishi-e looked visibly depressed, didn't she?
あの時、帰らなければ違う結果があったのだろうか……）
If I hadn't gone home back then, would things have turned out differently...?
一番良くないタイミングで帰っちゃった。
I chose the absolute worst timing to go home.
切ないのじゃ。なんか順番があったな。
There was an order to these!
順番があったな。
There was an order!
エンディング全部回収しましたのじゃ。
I collected all the endings, you see.
したけど、したけど、
Even so...
エンディング回収ってこんな辛い作業なんだ！知らなかった！
I didn't know that collecting endings could be such painful work!
知らなかった、もう一回ハッピーエンド見るか！もう一回ハッピーエンド見るか！
I didn't know. Let's watch the happy end again!
あの……嬉しいとこみよ。
Let's watch that happy ending again.
嬉しいとこみて、ちょちょちょ、嬉しい、その「帰る」を選択して
In that happy ending, when you choose to go home...
帰るを選択して……帰らないか。
Wait, you select go home, and then... wait, you don't go home?
はい、笑ってるーー！ムキムキ……ムキムキって……
She's laughing! "Muscular... muscular?"
「いっしゅめ」じゃん！おねーさんやばいー！
"It's an 'isshume'! Big sis, you're crazy!"
は～い♥
"Okay~!"
スー……はぁ……はぁ……
"*Huuu... haaa... haaa...*"
ごめんなさい。今日、私のお話にここまで付き合って下さって……
"I'm sorry for making you listen to my story for so long today..."
もしよろしければ、ここで解散にしませんか？
"If you don't mind, shall we part ways here?"
栗志江さん♥
"Kurie-san..."
は、はいっ♥
"Y-Yes...!"
ベンチで休まない？……帰らないのじゃあ……
"Would you like to rest on a bench?... I'm not going home..."
栗志江さんって、中学までどんな感じだったの？
"What was your life like up until middle school, Kurie-san?"
両親の都合で、今年3月まで欧州にいました。小中は全寮制の女子校でしたね……
"Due to my parents' work, I lived in Europe until March of this year. Both elementary and middle school were all-girls boarding schools..."
あ、帰国子女なんだ♥ 和菓子にピンと来なかったのはそういう訳か。
"Ah, you're a returnee. That's why Japanese sweets didn't ring a bell."
前は、校則が厳しくて、TVもスマホも禁止。娯楽はドラえもんとかアンパンマンの本だけでした♥
"Before, the school rules were strict, and TV and smartphones were banned. Entertainment was just books of Doraemon and Anpanman."
でも今年、日本に帰ることになったので父を説得して公立高校に進学したんです♥
"But since we were moving back to Japan this year, I persuaded my father and enrolled in a public high school."
父を説得して……だって、箱入り娘なわけでしょう？
"I persuaded my father... After all, I was a sheltered daughter, right?"
父を説得して公立高校に進学した結果、さっきみたいに嫌な陰口言われるんでしょ？泣いちゃうけどね♥
"As a result of persuading my father to go to a public high school, do you think I'd get nasty gossip behind my back like earlier? Though I'd cry..."
楽しみにしてた世界が、実はすごい意地悪なものでしたって……
"Finding out that the world I was looking forward to was actually so mean..."
大豪遊じゃけど絶望じゃけど世界が嫌になっちゃうけどね♥ねえ、父に意見とかあんましなさそうなのにね♥嫌な話なのじゃん。
"It's a huge luxury, but also despair, making me hate the world... Hey, even though you don't seem like you'd give your father lip, it's an unpleasant story."
へえ。スマホは持ってたよね。それも解禁されたの？やっぱ私立に行くのじゃお嬢様はね♥お嬢様はお嬢様と一緒にいた方がたぶんいい。
"Hee. You had a smartphone. Was that also unlocked? Naturally, going to a private school, a young lady... A young lady is probably better off staying with other young ladies."
スマホも解禁されて、普通の学生生活が送れるようになったんです！嬉しいのじゃ♥
"Smartphones were unlocked too, and I became able to live a normal student life! I'm so happy!"
それで春休みは行きたいお店とイベントに全部行って、映画とドラマ三昧で……♥
"So during spring break, I went to all the shops and events I wanted to go to, and binged movies and dramas..."
この春休みは、初めて知ることがたくさんありました！初めて知った嬉しかったことをマジで教えてくれたんでしょ？いい子じゃんか♥
"This spring break, I learned so many new things! You seriously told me about the things you were happy to learn for the first time, didn't you? What a good girl."
いい子なのだじゃ♥かき氷シロップね♥わしがかき氷買ってきてあげるから。
"You're a good girl. Shaved ice syrup... I'll buy you some shaved ice."
毎日新しい発見があって、楽しかった。いいことじゃあ♥いいことなのだじゃ。でも……
"Every day had new discoveries, and it was fun. That's a good thing... That's a good thing. But..."
新しい発見だと思っていたのは、私だけだったんです♥そんなことないよ！
"Thinking it was a new discovery... I was the only one who thought that! There's no such thing!"
（……そういえば、先週、隣の席で女子3人が何か言ってたな）
"(...Come to think of it, last week, three girls at the next desk were saying something.)"
女子1: 栗志江さん、どう？♥
"Kurie-san, how is she?"
女子2: ん……悪い子じゃないけど……つまんないかも♥
"Hmm... She's not a bad girl, but... maybe boring."
女子3: それ！知ってる話しかしないよね！♥ 厳しいのじゃ。
"Exactly! She only talks about things she already knows! That's harsh."
いいだろ別に！
"So what, leave me alone!"
てかんながこっちの方が社会性ないのじゃ♥こっちの方が社会性ないのじゃ♥
"I mean, if anything, you guys are the ones lacking social skills!"
人間社会なんてさぁ……あ、それ知ってるな！っていう話をさぁ
"In human society... like, talking about things 'ah, I know that!'"
人間社会のコミュニケーションってさぁ、敵意がないことを示すためにする会話じゃろ？
"Human communication is just conversation to show you have no hostility, right?"
別にその会話でに、その体現価値を見出そうとしてないのじゃ人間って♥人間はただ
"People aren't trying to find some profound value in those conversations. Humans just..."
いや、この群れに属すために、私は敵意がないことを証明しますよ！てのをアピールするためだけの手段として
"No, as a mere means to appeal 'I will prove I have no hostility in order to belong to this herd!'"
こういうコミュニケーションをとってるから♥なんかそれを肯定しない方が社会性ないのじゃ♥
"They have this kind of communication... so not affirming that is what lacks social skills!"
うん。そういうもんなのじゃ♥やばくないのじゃ♥厳しいのじゃ♥
"Yeah. That's just how it is... It's not crazy... It's harsh."
（……栗志江さんをそう評価する生徒もいた）
"(...There were students who evaluated Kurie-san like that.)"
（うちのクラス、ある種の態度にやたら厳しい人が多いし……）
"(In our class, many people are unusually strict about certain attitudes...)"
私の発見は……面白くもなんともなかった♥そんなことないよ！
"My discovery... wasn't interesting at all! There's no such thing!"
周回遅れなんて……そんなことないよ！
"Being a lap behind... There's no such thing!"
やっぱ人には人の初めてがあるから♥人には人の初めてがあるから♥肯定しなきゃ♥
"After all, everyone has their own 'first times'... You have to affirm them!"
ねぇ、それで遊んでくれたわけでしょう？うれしいでしょ？
"Hey, they played with you because of that, right? Aren't you happy?"
それで……手垢のついた、つまらないことばかり言ってしまった♥それがコミュニケーションですのじゃ♥それも含めて許容するのがコミュニケーションですのじゃ♥
"Then... I ended up saying nothing but clichéd, boring things... That's what communication is! Accepting all of that is what communication is!"
鈍いわけじゃない♥自分もそうだよ♥栗志江さん……
"It's not that you're dense... I am too... Kurie-san..."
鈍いわけじゃないよ！だってその……知る機会がなかったんでしょ？
"It's not that you're dense! After all... you didn't have the chance to know, right?"
まあ、そうかもしれません。皆さんはどこで学ぶのでしょうか♥本当だよな♥誰が教えてくれるのじゃコミュニケーションって♥体当たりで知っていくしかないのじゃ♥
"Well, that may be so. Where do you all learn? That's true... Who teaches you what communication is? You just have to learn by throwing yourself into it."
自分は「○○あるある」系のショートにハマってた時があったよ♥あるある系はね♥鉄板なのじゃ♥全人類に刺さるからね♥やり得なのだじゃ♥やり得なのだじゃ♥だからわしも初配信で「あるある」を入れたのじゃ♥
"I was once hooked on 'so-and-so relatability' shorts. Relatable stuff... is a classic! Because it hits all of humanity. It's a sure win! That's why I included 'relatable things' in my first stream too!"
ああ、そういったものはありますね♥そうなのじゃ♥わかってくる♥流行ってるやつの真似じゃん♥ねえ、そんなこと言わないで♥そのうちネットじゃ、何を見ても既視感しかなくなってきて……
"Ah, those things exist. That's right... You start to understand. It's just mimicking what's trendy... Hey, don't say that... Eventually on the net, no matter what you see, it just feels like déjà vu..."
そのうちネットじゃ、何を見ても、既視感しかなくなってきて……
Before long, on the net, whatever you see gives you a sense of déjà vu...
栗志江さん……？
Kurishie-san...?
おかげで使い古された表現には詳しくなったけど、今度は怖くなったのじゃ。
Thanks to that, I'm well-versed in clichéd expressions, but now I'm scared.
びびってますよと。
Like, you're terrified.
そうなのじゃ。
That's right.
お前は俺だ。俺はお前なのじゃ。
You are me. I am you.
ふーん。
Hmm.
自分の言った感想や意見が、手垢のついた話だったらどうしよう？って。
What if my thoughts and opinions are just common, worn-out cliches?
そんなびびることないと思うけどな。
I don't think you need to be that scared, though.
環境が悪い。
The environment is bad.
てか何かそれであの不安になるような環境ならもうパパに言って転校させてもらおう？
Or if the environment makes you that anxious, why not ask your dad to let you transfer schools?
学校が悪いのじゃ。いじめすぎますのじゃ。
The school is bad. They're bullying you too much.
それで、映画の感想も、明確には言ってくれなかったんですね。
And so, you didn't give a clear opinion on the movie either.
だってモカもだけどさ、クリシエもさぁ、あのさぁ……
Because, I mean, Moka too, and Kurishie too, you know...
あの、メラオも割と被害者だよね。メラオもそれで感想言えなくなっちゃったんでしょ？
Um, Mela-o is pretty much a victim too. Mela-o couldn't give impressions because of that too, right?
もう悪じゃん！学校が悪なのじゃ！
That's already evil! The school is evil!
学校が悪なのじゃ！転校しよう！
The school is evil! Let's transfer!
だから……栗志江さんははめあいみたいに気にしすぎないでほしいんだ。
That's why... I don't want Kurishie-san to worry too much about it like Hameai.
確かにもう誰かが見つけたかもしれないけど、栗志江さんが自分で発見したでしょ？
Sure, someone else might have found it already, but Kurishie-san discovered it yourself, right?
それは「つまらないこと」なんかじゃないよ！尊いことなのじゃ。
That's not something 'boring'! It's a precious thing.
お気遣い、ありがとうございます。
Thank you for your concern.
（気を遣わせてるのは、こっちだ）
(I'm the one making you worry.)
（こんな……それこそ、どこかで聞いたような）
(Such... exactly, something I've heard somewhere before)
メラオ、かき氷持ってくるよ。かき氷持っていくよ！
Mela-o, I'll bring shaved ice. I'm going to bring shaved ice!
じゃじゃーん！かき氷の、じゃあ、狂ったかき氷の、じゃあ……
Ta-da! For the shaved ice, well, for the crazy shaved ice, well...
かき氷のシロップはどれも同じ味だっていうのは、知ってる……知ってるつもりだった。
Knowing that shaved ice syrups all taste the same... or so I thought I knew.
超冷たい。冷めて、冷て、サムム、メラ、サムムメラ！
Super cold. Cold, cold, samumu, mera, samumu mera!
でも、それは漫画とネットで見て知った気になってるだけなんだ。
But that was just feeling like I knew it from manga and the internet.
本当に味が同じなのか、自分で確認したことはない。試してみた！
I've never checked for myself if the flavors are really the same. I tried it!
だから今、試す！！
That's why I'm trying it right now!!
ああっ！そんなペースで……！
Ahhh! At that pace...!
すごいペースで食べる。びっくりしてる。そんなペースで食べるんじゃないよと。
Eating at an amazing pace. I'm surprised. Don't eat at a pace like that.
イチゴ味とメロン味か。確かにあまり違いはないか？
Strawberry flavor and melon flavor. Is there really not much difference?
のじゃ。いや、舌が冷えてわからなくなってきた……
No ja. No, my tongue is getting cold and I can't tell anymore...
ううっ、寒い！歯がいたい！
Ugh, it's cold! My teeth hurt!
大変！上着あるので着てください。うわ、ラブコメじゃの！ほっこりじゃの！お似合いじゃの！
Oh no! Please put on a jacket since I have one. Wow, what a romantic comedy! So heartwarming! You two look great together!
ありがとう、栗志江さん♡
Thank you, Kurishie-san ♡
私も、何度か違う味のかき氷を食べるうちに違和感を覚えたので、食べ比べをしたんですが……栗志江さんも食べ比べをしています。
I also felt a sense of discord while eating shaved ice of different flavors a few times, so I compared them... and Kurishie-san is also comparing them.
栗志江さん行動派なのじゃ！あるあるを見てね、食べ比べをまだ実際にじゃやってみよう本当にどうなのかなって疑問を持つ人あんまりいないのじゃ。
Kurishie-san is a person of action! Looking at tropes, not many people actually try to compare them to see what it's really like.
ショートで流れてきたことはふーんでその場で忘れるのじゃ基本的に。
Things that appear in shorts, you basically forget on the spot with a 'hmm'.
試すまでいくのは相当な、そこまでいったらもう趣味でいいのじゃ。
Going as far as trying it is quite something, if you go that far, it's fine as a hobby.
検証するのすごいのじゃ……
Verifying it is amazing...
そ、そうですか？うん！……ああ、くち冷たい……
I-Is that so? Yeah! ......Ah, my mouth is cold...
いい空気味！
Good air flavor!
ね、知的好奇心高いよね。
Right, high intellectual curiosity.
いいね。
Nice.
栗志江さん、舌が緑！やったのじゃ！いいお話し！
Kurishie-san, your tongue is green! You did it! Good story!
（かき氷のメロン味で舌の色が……）
(The shaved ice melon flavor made my tongue color...)
（またベタなことしちゃったな）（まあ……でも……）
(I did a cliché thing again) (Well... but...)
（初めて栗志江さんの満面の笑みが見たし、いいか……）
(I saw Kurishie-san's full smile for the first time, so I guess it's fine...)
今日だるかったー！
Today was sluggish!
やっぱハッピーエンドしか勝たないのじゃ。
As expected, only happy endings win.
その、これから予定ありますか？部活とか、塾とか。
Um, do you have any plans for now? Like club activities, or cram school.
誘ってきた！好感度爆上がり！じゅわい！タピオカ屋さんに行きませんか！
She invited me! Favorability skyrocketing! Juwai! Won't you go to a tapioca shop with me!
友達とは行ったことないから、とか？
Because I've never been with friends, or something?
はい！……友達ならもうちょっと砕けた感じでもいいんじゃない？
Yes! ...Wouldn't it be better to be a bit more casual with friends?
あ……口調ですか？
Ah... tone?
一緒に行こ、めらお！行くのじゃーーっ！
Let's go together, Mela-o! We're goingーー!
やったー！ハッピーエンド！てあカノ。
Yay! Happy Ending! Teakano.
人には優しくしよう。ちょっとお話しするために部屋変わろうかな？お部屋変わりますのじ……
Be kind to people. Shall I change rooms to talk a bit? I'm changing rooms no ji...
部屋かので遊んだのじゃー
Playing "Heya Kano", noja!
なんか
Like...
わしもさ、
You know, when I
インターネット始めたての頃はさ、
first started using the internet back then,
結構苦労したけど、
I had a pretty hard time, but
インターネットってやっぱ どこにでも初見さんって居るのじゃ。
on the internet, there are newcomers everywhere, you know.
どこにでも初見さんって居るから、
Since there are newcomers everywhere—
ちょっと待って、きのこだけの子ちょっと消すか。
Wait, let's delete the mushroom-only ones for a sec.
一旦これ消すか。
Let's delete this for now.
一旦これ争いを生むものは消すのじゃ。
Let's delete anything that causes conflict.
で高評価を促すのじゃ。
And then encourage likes, noja!
うん、ちょっと一旦ね。
Yeah, hold on a second.
そういえば忘れしてたのじゃ。
Come to think of it, I forgot.
ストーリーを見てて忘れていた。
I was watching the story and forgot.
忘れてたのじゃ。
I forgot, noja!
恐ろしいのじゃ。
It's terrifying, noja.
キノコルート見ないのじゃ。
Don't look at the mushroom route!
もう配信で触っている以上ね、
Well, since we're already playing it on stream,
配信で触っている以上ね、
since we're touching it on stream,
でどっちなのじゃって。
and which one is it, you ask?
炎オガマがいますのじゃ。
There's a Flame Ogame, noja.
だめなのじゃ。
That's no good, noja.
だめですのじゃ。
It's no good, noja.
答えませんのじゃ。
I won't answer, noja.
沈黙。
Silence.
沈黙なのだ。
It's silence.
目撃意見講師しますのじゃ。
I will lecture on eyewitness accounts, noja.
のじゃ。炎魔？
Noja. Flame Demon?
どっちじゃ？
Which is it?
炎魔のピコ？
Flame Demon's pico?
神回避！
God dodge!
ね、朝、朝のノジャイングリッシュでちょうどその話したから、あの、
You know, in the morning, in morning Noja English, I was just talking about that, so, um,
伏線回収みたいだったのじゃ。
it felt like foreshadowing resolution, noja.
ちょっとやっぱあのVTuberとして表に出ているホロライブ所属のアチチメラとしての見解を出すことはちょっと控ええますのじゃ。
Still, as a VTuber and Hololive-affiliated Achichi Mera, I'll refrain from giving my views on that, noja.
友達とかと話すときは話すかもしれないけど、
I might talk about it when I'm chatting with friends,
VTuberとしてね、お話ししてしまうとね、ちょっとなかなか、
but as a VTuber, if I talk about it... it's pretty hard, you know.
なかなかね、
Pretty hard,
ですのじゃ。
it is, noja.
またのはいけない、エコクロスはきつい。
Can't do that again, echo cross is tough.
評価はね、おかしかったりはいけないね。
As for evaluations, it shouldn't be weird.
面白かった、ノベルゲー初めてだったけど、
It was interesting. It was my first visual novel, but
こういう感じなんだな。これ、これで覚えちゃダメか？
so this is what it's like. Can't I just learn from this?
基本帰れないか。基本帰れないで、
You essentially can't go back, right? You can't go back,
買い物の選択肢で分岐してく感じか？
and it branches based on shopping choices?
そんな感じな気がしたのじゃ。ノベルゲーの面白かったのじゃ。
That's the kind of vibe I got, noja. Visual novels are fun, noja.
ここまで見なかったのじゃ。
I hadn't seen this far, noja.
難しかったのじゃ。
It was difficult, noja.
でも、やっぱ、帰るって最悪。
But still, going back is the worst.
帰るって最悪なのじゃ。
Going back is the worst, noja.
傷つく。
It hurts.
てか、誘ったのに、
I mean, after inviting them,
誘って帰るって一番失礼じゃない？
inviting someone and then leaving is the most rude thing ever, right?
なら誘うなよって思わん？
Don't you think "Then don't invite me"?
だって、きっとなんか可愛いなとかさ。
Like, they must think "how cute" or something.
可愛いなどこかで誘ってさ、
Inviting them somewhere because they're cute,
ああ、可愛いだけかよで帰るのってガチカス、クズ、クズ男すぎない？
and then going "Oh, she's just cute" and leaving... Isn't that totally trash, scum, super scum guy?
メラをクズ男すぎない？
Isn't Mera being too much of a scum guy?
そんなの良くないのじゃ。
That's not good, noja.
自分の決断に責任を持つのじゃ。
Take responsibility for your own decisions, noja.
クリスさん傷ついちゃったよだって。
Chris-san got hurt, they say.
そう。相手の全部を受け止める
Yeah. You gotta be ready to accept
覚悟で誘わないと。
everything about the other person.
で、なんかその全部を受け入れられるほどの関係値とか、
And like, having enough relationship value to accept all of that,
知らない子を誘うんだっていう話ではあるな。
or inviting someone you don't know...
知らないのに誘っちゃダメなのじゃ。
You shouldn't invite someone you don't know, noja.
ね、かわいそうだった。
You know, it was pitiful.
クラちゃんかわいそうだった。
Kura-chan was pitiful.
まあでもそれがいいゲームデザイン。
Well, but that's good game design.
すぐ出れなかったのに、あそこね。
Even though you couldn't get out right away, right there.
これだからオタク君は、のじゃー！
That's why you otaku guys are— Noja!
なんか最初の方結構きつかったんだよな。
The beginning part was pretty tough, you know.
自分の黒歴史が、黒歴史っていうか なんか
My own dark history, or rather, like...
こ れってわしのことだ、って思っちゃって、
thinking "This is about me,"
切なかったけど。
it was heartbreaking, but...
ダメージが自分に刺さる、刺さりまくったのじゃ。
The damage hit me, it kept piercing me, noja.
こういう時代あったな。わしにもこういうことあったな、って思った。
There was a time like this. I thought, "I had times like this too."
霊傷良くない。
Psychic scars are no good.
人が面白いと思っているものを、こばかにして笑うの良くない。
Making fun of what people find interesting and laughing is no good.
当たり前です。良くないのじゃ。
That's obvious. It's no good, noja.
でも、正直、
But honestly,
若さってある。正直、そういうなんだろうな、思春期...
youth exists. Honestly, that kind of, what is it, puberty...
中二病とかさ、そういうのって正直通ると思うのじゃ。
Things like chuunibyou... I think everyone honestly goes through that phase.
そういう時期ってあるから、誰にでもあるから、その時期を否定することはしないけど、
That phase happens to everyone, so I'm not going to deny it, but...
なんか大人になって、あーあの頃の自分がいたかったなとか、あれは良くなかったなって思えてたらオッケーな気がする。
When you grow up and think, "Ah, I wanted to be like that back then," or "That wasn't good," if you can realize that, I think you're okay.
思えてたら、それはもう成長なのだじゃ。そういう時期はある。
If you can realize that, that's already growth. That phase definitely exists.
あるし思うことはあっても、それを表に出さなければいい気がする。
Even if you feel that way, I feel like you just shouldn't show it outwardly.
逆張りレイショーが別に悪いわけじゃなくて、それをなんだろう、人に押し付けたりするから良くないのじゃ。
Being contrarian isn't inherently bad. It's just bad when you try to force it onto other people.
うん、心の中でね、思ってる分にはさ、別いいからな。
Yeah, keeping those thoughts to yourself is totally fine, you know.
私なんかこの冷笑とか逆張りって割と自分の心を守るためにすることってない？かも。
For me, isn't being cynical or contrarian often a way to protect your own heart? Maybe.
それをすることで自分の心を守っている節があると思っているのじゃ。
I feel like doing that has a way of protecting my own heart.
そのスターバックスとか、なんか誘ってもらえなかったから、1人だけ誘ってもらえなくて寂しくて、寂しいから武装するみたいな。そう予防線を張ってくみたいな。
Like with Starbucks, when you weren't invited, you felt left out and lonely, so you arm yourself. Putting up preventive defenses like that.
自分のなかで言い訳をしてるみたいな。別に興味ないしそんなのだから誘われなくていいもんみたいな。
Making excuses to yourself like, "I'm not even interested anyway, so I don't need to be invited."
そういうことをわしあったから反省なのだじゃ。
I've experienced things like that myself, so I reflect on it.
人間関係でダメージを受けるからむやみに他人の言う自分を信じたり、それを…
To avoid getting hurt in relationships, you might blindly believe what others say about you, or...
だから、まあ、なんじゃろうな。
So, yeah, what is it?
まあ、他人を傷つけない。態度に出さない！態度に出さない！1周目の人には優しくする。自分もそういう時期があったのだから。
Well, don't hurt others. Don't show it in your attitude! Don't show it! Be kind to newcomers, because you went through that phase too.
お！いい気付きじゃの。わしもわしもちのその領域にたどり着いたことがあったよって優しく受け入れるのじゃ。
Oh! That's a great realization. Welcoming them gently by saying, "I've reached that territory too, you know."
おのしらもね、あの、やっぱVTuber初めて見ますとかそういうなんかはじめましてさんは今後いっぱい出会っていくと思うけど優しくしよう。優しくね。
And for you guys too, you'll meet lots of "nice to meet you" VTuber beginners in the future, so let's be kind. Be kind, okay?
ああ、あったあった自分もそういうことが。そしてできるだけ優しく教えてあげるのじゃ。そうすることで優しく教えられた人は次の新人の人に優しくなる気がする。優しさの連鎖なのだじゃ。
Ah, yeah, I had moments like that too. And I try to teach them as gently as possible. That way, those who are taught kindly will likely be kind to the next newcomers. It's a chain of kindness.
のじゃ。わしもう新人じゃよ！わしもう新人VTuberじゃから優しくしてほしいのじゃあ！優しくして！優しさしてほしいのって言われてる。もうすでにされてますのじゃ。
Indeed! I'm a newcomer too! I'm a newcomer VTuber so I want you to be gentle with me! "Please be gentle," someone says. You're already doing it!
優しくしてほしいのもされてる。もうすでにされてますのじゃ。うん。ありがとなのじゃ。
Wanting to be treated kindly... you're already doing it. Yeah, thank you so much.
そろそろおしまい予定日じゃお。明日は8時からソピアと遊びたいぜんで遊びますのじゃ。9日は遊びまわりタイでクイズの企画やりますのじゃ。
It's almost time to wrap up. Tomorrow starting at 8 PM, I'll be playing with Sopiah. On the 9th, I'll be doing a quiz event in "Let's Play Around."
10日の19時からはスパゲット、スパゲッティのゲームっぽい。何のゲームかはあんまり分かってないんじゃけど、フブキ先輩がくださったゲームなのだじゃ。11日はリズム天国がありますのじゃ。
On the 10th from 7 PM, it's SPAGHET, looks like a spaghetti game. I don't really know what kind of game it is, but Fubuki-senpai gave it to me. On the 11th, we have Rhythm Heaven.
お楽しみに！お楽しみに！ふん。のじゃ。スパゲット、お楽しみリベンジ！イグノーベル？
Look forward to it! Look forward to it! Hmm. SPAGHET, looking forward to the revenge! Ig Nobel?
じゃあお主ら、また明日の配信で会おうね。挨拶はバイバイのじゃでいきますのじゃ。行くのじゃ。バイバイのじゃじゃなくて、さらばじゃだ。
Alright everyone, let's meet again in tomorrow's stream. The greeting will be "Bye-bye noja!" Let's go. Not "Bye-bye noja," but "Farewell noja!"
挨拶はさらばじゃで行くのじゃ！行くのじゃお主ら！さらばじゃあ！
The greeting is "Farewell"! Let's go everyone! Farewell!